<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A phenix, or, The Solemn League and Covenant whereunto is annexed : 1. The form and manner of His Majesties coronation in Scotland, with a sermon then preached on that occasion, by Robert Douglas of Edenburgh, II. A declaration of the Kings Majesty to all his loving subjects of the Kingdoms of Scotland, &amp;c. in the yeare 1650, III. The great danger of covenant-breaking, &amp;c., being the substance of a sermon preached by Edm. Calamy, the 14 of Jan., 1645, before the then Lord Mayor of the city of London, Sir Tho. Adams : together with the shieriffs [sic], aldermen, and Common-Councell of the said city : being the day of their taking the Solemn League and Covenant at Michael Basenshaw, London.</title>
            <author>Douglas, Robert, 1594-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36441</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5271</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12986268</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12986268</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96187</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36441)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96187)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 736:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A phenix, or, The Solemn League and Covenant whereunto is annexed : 1. The form and manner of His Majesties coronation in Scotland, with a sermon then preached on that occasion, by Robert Douglas of Edenburgh, II. A declaration of the Kings Majesty to all his loving subjects of the Kingdoms of Scotland, &amp;c. in the yeare 1650, III. The great danger of covenant-breaking, &amp;c., being the substance of a sermon preached by Edm. Calamy, the 14 of Jan., 1645, before the then Lord Mayor of the city of London, Sir Tho. Adams : together with the shieriffs [sic], aldermen, and Common-Councell of the said city : being the day of their taking the Solemn League and Covenant at Michael Basenshaw, London.</title>
                  <author>Douglas, Robert, 1594-1674.</author>
                  <author>Calamy, Edmund, 1600-1666. Great danger of covenant-breaking.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 168 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.], Printed in the year of covenant-breaking,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1662?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: illus. lacking in filmed copy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Coronation.</term>
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96187:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96187:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A PHENIX, OR, The Solemn LEAGUE and COVENANT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto is annexed,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>I.</hi> The Form and manner of His Majeſties Coronation in <hi>Scotland.</hi> With a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon then preached on that occaſion, by <hi>Robert Douglas</hi> of <hi>Edenburgh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>II.</hi> A Declaration of the Kings Majeſty to all His loving Subjects of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;c. in the Yeare <hi>1650.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>III.</hi> The great Danger of Covenant-breaking, &amp;c. Being the ſubſtance of a Sermon preached by <hi>Edm. Calamy</hi> the <hi>14.</hi> of Jan. <hi>1645.</hi> before the then Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho. Adams,</hi> together with the Shieriffs, Aldermen, and Common-councell of the ſaid City: being the day of their taking the Solemn League and Covenant at <hi>Michael Baſenſhaw,</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH, <hi>Printed in the year of Covenant-breaking.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:96187:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96187:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou mayſt expect ſome Reaſons (by way of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face) why theſe things thus collected are preſented to thy conſideration, the principall part thereof having been the occaſion of ſo much conteſt and trouble in theſe Nations, and therefore deſired by many it ſhould have been buried in its own aſhes. But for that things of ſuch publique concernment, have been acted by the Heads of theſe Nations, and in ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn a manner, in the preſence
<pb facs="tcp:96187:3"/> of Almighty God, it cannot ſo ſoon be forgotten, but ought to be weighed, and layd to heart, with the good or evil conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences that have or ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crew thereby, it is therefore left to thy ſerious conſideration.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="covenant">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96187:3"/>
            <head>A ſolemn <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Covenant:</hi> For Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and defence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: the Honour and Happines of the <hi>King,</hi> and the Peace and Safety of the three Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE the Noblemen, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, Burgeſſes, Miniſters of the Goſpel, and Commons of all ſorts in the Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the providence of God living under one King and being of one Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion, having before our Eyes the glory of God, and the advancement of the Kingdom of our Lord &amp; Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, the Honour and Happineſs of the Kings Majeſty, and his Poſterity, and the true Publick Liberty, Safety &amp; peace of the Kingdoms,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96187:4"/> wherein every ones private condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is included; &amp; calling to mind the treacherous and bloody Plots, Conſpiracies, Attempts, &amp; Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Enemies of God, againſt the true Religion, and Profeſſors thereof in all places, eſpecially in theſe three Kingdoms, ever ſince the Reformation of Religion, and how much their Rage, Power, and Preſumption are of late, and at this time increaſed and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; whereof the deplorable eſtate of the Church and Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the diſtreſſed eſtate of the Church and Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the dangerous eſtate of the Church &amp; Kingdom of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> are preſent and publick Teſtimonies. We have now at laſt (after other means of Supplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Remonſtrance, Proteſtations, and Sufferings,) for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our Selves and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion from utter ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96187:4"/> according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable practice of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms in former times, and the example of Gods people in other Nations, after mature deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, reſolved and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to enter into a Mutuall and Solemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, wherein we all ſubſcribe, and each one of us for himſelf, with our hands lifted up to the moſt high God, do ſwear:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1. THat we ſhall ſincerely, really, and conſtantly, through the grace of God, endeavour in our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall places and callings, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the reformed Religion in the Church of</hi> Scotland, <hi>in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, according to the Word of God, and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches: And ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to bring the Churches of God in the three kingdoms to the neareſt conjunction and unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in religion, confeſſion of faith,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96187:5"/> form of Church-government, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory for worſhip and catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: That we and our poſterity after us may as brethren live in faith and love, and the Lord may delight to dwell in the midſt of us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2. That we ſhall in like manner without reſpect of perſons, endeavor the extirpation of popery, prelacy, (that is, Church-government by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, their Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, and Commiſſaries, Deans, Deans and Chapters, Archdeacons, and all other Eccleſiaſticall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers depending on that Hierarchy) ſuperſtition, hereſie, ſchiſm, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanneſs, and whatſoever ſhall be found to be contrary to ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and the power of godlineſs; leſt we partake in other mens ſins, and therein be in danger to receive of their plagues, and that the Lord may be one, and his Name one in the three Kingdoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3. We ſhall with the ſame ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, reality and conſtancy, in our ſeverall vocations, endeavour with our eſtates and lives, mutually to preſerve the rights and priviledges
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96187:5"/> of the parliaments, and the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the kingdomes, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and defend the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Perſon and Authority, in the Preſervation and Defence of the true Religion, and Liberties of the Kingdomes, that the World may bear witneſſe with our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of our Loyalty, and that we have no thoughts or intentions to diminiſh His Majeſties juſt Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Greatneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4. We ſhall alſo with all Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe endeavour the diſcovery of all ſuch as have been, or ſhall be Incendiaries, Malignants, or evil Inſtruments, by hindering the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion, dividing the King from His People, or one of the three Kingdomes from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or making any faction or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties among the People, contrary to this League and Covenant, that they may be brought to publick Tryal, and receive condign Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the degree of their Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhall require or deſerve, or the Supream Judicatories of both Kingdomes reſpectively, or others
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96187:6"/> having power from them for that effect ſhall judge convenient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5. And whereas the Happineſſe of a bleſſed Peace between theſe Kingdomes, denied in former times to our Progenitors, is by the good Providence of God granted unto us, and hath been lately concluded, and ſetled by both the Parliaments, we ſhall each one of us, according to our place and intereſt, endeavour that they may remain conjoyned in a firm Peace and Union to all Poſterity, and that Juſtice may be done upon the wilfull oppoſers thereof, in manner expreſſed in the precedent Articles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6. We ſhall alſo according to our places and callings in this common cauſe of Religion, Liberty, and Peace of the Kingdomes, aſſiſt and defend all thoſe that enter into this League and Covenant, in the maintaining and purſuing thereof, and ſhall not ſuffer our ſelves di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly by whatſoever combination, perſwaſion, or ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, to be divided and withdrawn from this bleſſed Union and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96187:6"/> whether to make defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the contrary part, or to give our ſelves to a deteſtable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency or neutrality in this cauſe, which ſo much concerneth the glory of God, the good of the Kingdomes, and the honour of the King; but ſhall all the dayes of our lives, zealouſly, and conſtantly continue therein, againſt all oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and promote the ſame accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our power, againſt all lets and impediments whatſoever; and what we are not able our ſelves to ſuppreſſe or overcome, we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal and make known, that it may be timely prevented or removed; All which we ſhall do as in the ſight of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe theſe Kingdomes are guilty of many ſins and provocations againſt God, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, as is too manifeſt by our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſtreſſes and dangers, the fruits thereof: We profeſſe and declare before God and the world our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained deſire to be humbled for our own ſins, and for the ſins of theſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96187:7"/> Kingdomes, eſpecially that we have not as we ought, valued the ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble benefit of the Goſpel, that we have not laboured for the purity and power thereof, and that we have not endeavoured to receive Chriſt in our hearts, nor to walk worthy of him in our lives, which are the cauſes of our ſins and tranſgreſſions ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding amongſt us; and our true and unfained purpoſe, deſire, and endeavour for our ſelves, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers under our power and charge, both in publick and in private, in all duties we owe to God and Man to amend our lives, and each one to go before another in the example of a real Reformation, that the Lord may turn away his wrath and heavy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, and eſtabliſh theſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and Kingdomes in truth and peace. And this Covenant we make in the preſence of Almighty God the Searcher of all hearts, with a true intention to perform the ſame, as we ſhall anſwer at the great Day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed: Moſt humbly beſeeching the Lord to ſtrengthen us by his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96187:7"/> Spirit for this end, and to bleſſe our deſires and proceedings with ſuch ſucceſſe, as may be deliverance and ſafety to his people, and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to other Chriſtian Churches, groaning under, or in danger of the yoak of Antichriſtian tyranny: to joyn in the ſame or like Aſſociation and Covonant, to the glory of God, the enlargement of the Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt, and the peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of Chriſtian Kingdomes and Common-wealths.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Wil. Lenthal, <hi>Speaker</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Beuchamp St. John</item>
               <item>Gilbert Gerrard</item>
               <item>Walter Earle</item>
               <item>James Cambel</item>
               <item>Thomas Cheeke.</item>
               <item>Robert Nicholas</item>
               <item>Benjamin Rudyard</item>
               <item>John Gurdon</item>
               <item>Robert Harley</item>
               <item>Francis Knollis</item>
               <item>Edward Maſter</item>
               <item>John White</item>
               <item>Anthony Sapley</item>
               <item>Dennis Bond</item>
               <item>Lawrence Whitaker</item>
               <item>Michael Noble</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere. Hoby</item>
               <item>Richard Barwis</item>
               <item>Edward Baynton</item>
               <item>William Cawley</item>
               <item>John Moyle</item>
               <item>John Pyne</item>
               <item>George Searle</item>
               <item>Henry Vane <hi>ſenior</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Nevil Pool</item>
               <item>John Young</item>
               <item>Henry Herbert</item>
               <item>Thomas Sandys</item>
               <item>William Ieſſon</item>
               <item>Philip <hi>L.</hi> Herbert</item>
               <item>Thomas Bartington</item>
               <item>Martin Lumley</item>
               <item>John Trevor</item>
               <item>Francis Godolphin</item>
               <item>Thomas Arundell</item>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96187:8"/>
               <item>Edward Stephens</item>
               <item>Gilbert Piekering</item>
               <item>John Greve</item>
               <item>Oliver Cromwell</item>
               <item>Henry Vane <hi>junior</hi>
               </item>
               <item>William Cage</item>
               <item>Richard Eriſey</item>
               <item>Philip <hi>L.</hi> Liſle</item>
               <item>Will. Heveningham</item>
               <item>Iſaac Pennington</item>
               <item>Richard Creſheld</item>
               <item>Thomas Pelham</item>
               <item>Thomas Parker</item>
               <item>John Leigh</item>
               <item>John Harris</item>
               <item>Auguſtin Skinner</item>
               <item>John Venn</item>
               <item>William Strickland</item>
               <item>John Franklin</item>
               <item>Samuel Brown</item>
               <item>Robert Scawen</item>
               <item>Roger Hill</item>
               <item>John Button</item>
               <item>John Meyrick</item>
               <item>Ambroſe Brown</item>
               <item>Richard Winn</item>
               <item>Edward Owner</item>
               <item>Charles Pym</item>
               <item>Charles <hi>L.</hi> Cranborn</item>
               <item>Ben. Weſton</item>
               <item>Dudley North</item>
               <item>John Nut</item>
               <item>John Corbet</item>
               <item>Roger Burgoyne</item>
               <item>Peter Temple</item>
               <item>Benjamin Valentine</item>
               <item>Thomas Walſingham</item>
               <item>Oliver Luke</item>
               <item>William Alenſon</item>
               <item>Humphrey Salwey</item>
               <item>Richard Moor</item>
               <item>William Aſhurſt</item>
               <item>Thomas Moor</item>
               <item>Thomas Fountain</item>
               <item>William Ellys</item>
               <item>Henry Shelley</item>
               <item>Rich. Shuttleworth</item>
               <item>Henry Ludlow</item>
               <item>George Gallop</item>
               <item>Robert Wallop</item>
               <item>Arthur Heſilrige</item>
               <item>Oliver Saint-John</item>
               <item>Thomas Grantham</item>
               <item>Francis Barnham</item>
               <item>Will. L. Fitz Williams</item>
               <item>Edmund Dunch</item>
               <item>Henry Mildmay</item>
               <item>Hugh Rogers</item>
               <item>Thomas Hatcher</item>
               <item>John Wray</item>
               <item>Simonds D'Ewes</item>
               <item>Anthony Bedingfield</item>
               <item>John Aſhe</item>
               <item>William <hi>L.</hi> Munſon</item>
               <item>Martin Liſter</item>
               <item>Robert Goodwin</item>
               <item>Edward Thomas</item>
               <item>Henry Lucas</item>
               <item>Miles Corbet</item>
               <item>Philip Smith</item>
               <item>Cornelius Holland</item>
               <item>William Spurflowe</item>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96187:8"/>
               <item>John Lowry</item>
               <item>Peter Wentworth</item>
               <item>Henry Chomley</item>
               <item>Philip Stapleton</item>
               <item>William Pierrepoint</item>
               <item>Roger North</item>
               <item>Alexander Popham</item>
               <item>Thomas Hodges</item>
               <item>John Maynard</item>
               <item>Samuel Vaſſal</item>
               <item>Anthony Irby</item>
               <item>John Clotworthy</item>
               <item>John Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>lme</item>
               <item>Richard Jervoyſe</item>
               <item>John Blackiſton</item>
               <item>Walter Long</item>
               <item>John Rolle</item>
               <item>Robert Jennor</item>
               <item>John Waddon</item>
               <item>William Maſham</item>
               <item>John Liſle</item>
               <item>Edmund Fowel</item>
               <item>Edward Aſhe</item>
               <item>Thomas Pury</item>
               <item>Richard Whitehead</item>
               <item>Richard J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nyns</item>
               <item>Humphrey Tufton</item>
               <item>Thomas Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res</item>
               <item>Thomas Earl</item>
               <item>John Downes</item>
               <item>John Goodwyn</item>
               <item>Francis Drake</item>
               <item>William Waller</item>
               <item>Samuel Luke</item>
               <item>Francis Buller</item>
               <item>Richard Harman</item>
               <item>George Buller</item>
               <item>Arthur Onſlowe</item>
               <item>Richard Wynwood</item>
               <item>Robert Pye</item>
               <item>H. L. Gray of Ruthin</item>
               <item>Richard Knightley</item>
               <item>John Pym</item>
               <item>Chriſtoph. Yelverton</item>
               <item>Anthony Nicoll</item>
               <item>Peter Wroth</item>
               <item>Robert Reynolds</item>
               <item>Nat. Barnardiſton</item>
               <item>Henry Heyman</item>
               <item>William Purefoy</item>
               <item>Valentine Walton</item>
               <item>Michael Oldeſworth</item>
               <item>William Wheeler</item>
               <item>Hall Ravenſcroft</item>
               <item>T. <hi>L.</hi> Gray of Groby</item>
               <item>Thomas Middleton</item>
               <item>Edw. Hungerford</item>
               <item>Chriſtopher Wrey</item>
               <item>Richard Lee</item>
               <item>Herbert Morley</item>
               <item>Thomas Lane</item>
               <item>Robert Cecil</item>
               <item>William Bell</item>
               <item>Thomas Some</item>
               <item>Herbot. Grimſtone</item>
               <item>Symon Snowe</item>
               <item>John Naſh</item>
               <item>Herbot. Grimſtone</item>
               <item>Ralph Aſheton</item>
               <item>Edward Ayſhcoghe</item>
               <item>John Wylde</item>
               <item>John Trenchard</item>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96187:9"/>
               <item>Thomas Jervoyſe</item>
               <item>Richard Browne</item>
               <item>William Plaiters</item>
               <item>Nathaniel Stephens</item>
               <item>Richard Roſe</item>
               <item>Francis Rous</item>
               <item>Gilbert Millington</item>
               <item>Walter Young</item>
               <item>John Brown</item>
               <item>John Hippiſley</item>
               <item>Edward Poole</item>
               <item>Henry Pelham</item>
               <item>William Hay</item>
               <item>John Driden</item>
               <item>Nathaniel Fyennes;</item>
               <item>William Lewis</item>
               <item>Giles Grene</item>
               <item>William Lytton</item>
               <item>John Harvey.</item>
               <item>Edward Dowce</item>
               <item>William Strode</item>
               <item>Edmond Prideaux</item>
               <item>Thomas Hoyle</item>
               <item>Edward Exton</item>
               <item>Francis Popham</item>
               <item>Zouch Tate</item>
               <item>John Curſon</item>
               <item>Alexander Bence</item>
               <item>Squire Bence</item>
               <item>John Selden</item>
               <item>John Glyn</item>
               <item>Richard Onſlow</item>
               <item>John Coke</item>
               <item>Tho. L. Wenman</item>
               <item>Bulſtrode Whitlock</item>
               <item>George Montague</item>
               <item>Edward Partheriche</item>
               <item>Henry Campion</item>
               <item>VVilliam VVhittaker</item>
               <item>Denzel Holles</item>
               <item>Edward VVingate</item>
               <item>James Fennys</item>
               <item>Poynings Moore</item>
               <item>Edward Biſſe, <hi>junior.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VVilliam Jephſon</item>
               <item>Edward Montague</item>
               <item>Norton Knatchboll</item>
               <item>Thomas Eden</item>
               <item>Edward Baynton</item>
               <item>Jo. Evelin</item>
               <item>Jo. Potts</item>
               <item>Sam. Rolls</item>
               <item>Ralph Aſhton</item>
               <item>VVilliam Drake</item>
               <item>Pereg. Pelham</item>
               <item>VVilliam Brereton</item>
               <item>Thomas VViddrington</item>
               <item>Natha. Hallows</item>
               <item>Joh. Bamfield</item>
               <item>Symond Thelwall.</item>
               <item>Hen. VVorſley</item>
               <item>Phil. Parker</item>
               <item>Edw. Boys</item>
               <item>John Alford.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96187:9"/>
            <opener>
               <date>Die Veneris, <hi>29</hi> Januar. <hi>1644.</hi>
               </date>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, That the Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant be on every day of Faſt and Publique Humiliation, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely read in every Church and Congregation within the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: And that every Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be enjoyned to have one of the ſaid Covenants fairly Printed in a fair Letter, in a Table fitted to hang up in ſome publick place of the Church to be read.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen. Elſynge Cler. Pail. Dom. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96187:10"/>
            <head>The Form and Order of the CORONATION OF CHARLES II. King of <hi>Scotland, England, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> As it was acted and done at <hi>Scoon,</hi> the firſt day of <hi>January</hi> 1651.</head>
            <byline>By <hi>Robert Dowglas</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt the Kings Majeſty in a Princes Robe, was conducted from his Bed-chamber, by the Conſtable on his right hand, and the Marſhal on his left, to the Chamber of preſence; and there was placed in a Chair, under a cloth of State, by the Lord of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> Chamberlain appointed by the King for that day; and there, after a little repoſe, the Noblemen,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96187:10"/> with the Commiſſioners of Barons and Burroughs, entred the Hall, and preſented themſelves before his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Thereafter the Lord chancellor ſpoke to the King, to this purpoſe, <hi>Sir, your good Subjects deſire You may be crowned, as the righteous and lawful Heir of the Crown of this Kingdome; that you would maintain Religion, as it is preſently profeſſed and eſtabliſhed; conform to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional covenant, League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and according to your Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration at</hi> Dumferling <hi>in</hi> Auguſt <hi>laſt: Alſo that you would be graciouſly pleaſed to receive them under Your Highneſſe Protection, to govern them by the Lawes of the Kingdome, and to defend them in their Rights and Liberties, by Your Royal power; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering themſelves in moſt humble manner to Your Majeſty, with their vows, to beſtow land, life, and what elſe is in their power, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Religion, for the ſafety of Your Majeſties ſacred Perſon, and maintenance of Your Crown, which they intreat Your Majeſty to accept,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96187:11"/> and pray Almighty God, that for many Years You may happily enjoy the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King made this Anſwer; <hi>I do eſteem the affections of my good people, more than the Crowns of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Kingdomes, and ſhall be ready by Gods aſſiſtance, to beſtow my life in their Defence; Wiſhing to live no longer, than I may ſee Religion and this Kingdome flouriſh in all hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thereafter, the Commiſſioners of Burroughs and Barons, and the Noblemen, accompanied his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to the Kirk of <hi>Scoon,</hi> in order and rank, according to their qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, two and two. The Spurs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carried by the Earl of <hi>Eg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> Next, the Sword by the E. of <hi>Rothes.</hi> Then the Scepter, by the E. of <hi>Crauford</hi> and <hi>Lindeſay.</hi> And the Crown by Marq. of <hi>Argyle,</hi> immediately before the King. Then came the King, with the great Conſtable on his right hand, and the great Marſhal on his left; his train being carried by the L. <hi>Freskine,</hi> the L. <hi>Montgomery,</hi> the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96187:11"/> L. <hi>Newbottle,</hi> and the L. <hi>Machlene,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our Earls eldeſt ſons, under a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopy of crimſon Velvet, ſupported by ſix Earls ſons; to wit, the L. <hi>Drummond,</hi> the L. <hi>Carnegie,</hi> the L. <hi>Ramſey,</hi> the L. <hi>Johnſtoun,</hi> the the L <hi>Brechin,</hi> L. <hi>Yeſter;</hi> and the ſix Carriers ſupported by ſix No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemens ſons. Thus the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſty entred the Kirk.</p>
            <p>The Kirk being fitted and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, with a Table, whereupon the Honours were laid, and a Chair ſet in a fitting place for his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties hearing of Sermon, over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Miniſter, and another Chair on the other ſide where he received the Crown; before which there was a Bench, decently cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; as alſo for ſeats about, for No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen, Barons, and Burgeſſes. And there being alſo a Stage in a fit place erected, of 24 foot ſquare, about four foot high from the ground, covered with Carpets, with two ſtairs, one from the Weſt, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Eaſt; upon which great ſtage, there was another little ſtage erected, ſome two foot high, aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96187:12"/> by two ſteps; on which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Throne, or Chair of State wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſet.</p>
            <p>The Kirk thus fittingly prep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, the Kings Majeſty entre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſame, accompanied as afor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaid, and firſt ſetteth himſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> in his chair for hearing of Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon.</p>
            <p>All being quietly compoſe unto attention, Mr. <hi>Robert Dow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas,</hi> Moderator of the Gener<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Aſſembly, after incalling upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God by prayer, preached the fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowing Sermon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96187:12"/>
            <head>A Sermon preached at <hi>Scoon, Jan.</hi> 1. 1651. At the Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Seotland, England, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>By <hi>Robert Dowglas,</hi> Miniſter at <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinburgh,</hi> Moderator of the Commiſſion of the General Aſſembly.</byline>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 KINGS 11.</hi> Verſ. <hi>12.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And he brought forth the Kings Son, and put the Crown upon him, and gave him the Teſtimony; and they made him King, and anointed him, and they clape their hands and ſaid, God ſave the King.</p>
                  <p>And Jehojada made a Covenant between the Lord, and the King, and the People, that they ſhould be the Lords people, between the King alſo and the people.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN this Text of Scripture, you have the Solemn Enthronizing of <hi>Joaſh,</hi> a young King, and that in a very troubleſome time; for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaliah</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:96187:13"/> the mother of <hi>Ahaziah</hi> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cruelly murthered the Royal Seed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and uſurped the Kingdome, by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpace of ſix yeares. Onely thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> young Prince was preſerved by <hi>Iehoſheba</hi> the ſiſter of <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> and wife to <hi>Jehojada</hi> the high Prieſt, being hid with her in the houſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord all that time.</p>
            <p>Good Interpreters do conjecture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though <hi>Joaſh</hi> be called the ſon of <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> that he was not his ſon by nature, but by ſucceſſion to the Crown. They ſay, that the race of <hi>Solomon</hi> ceaſed here, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome came to the poſterity of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> the ſon of <hi>David.</hi> Becauſe 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.9. it is ſaid, <hi>The houſe of Ahaziah had no power to keep the Kingdome;</hi> which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be for the want of children in that houſe; And becauſe of the abſurdity and unnaturalneſſe of the fact, that <hi>Athaliah</hi> the Grand-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould have cut off her ſons children. I ſhall not ſtand upon the matter, only I may ſay, if they were <hi>Ahaziah</hi> his own children, it was a moſt unnatural and cruel
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96187:13"/> fact of <hi>Athaliah</hi> to cut off her own poſterity.</p>
            <p>For the uſurpation, there might have been two motives. 1. It ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that when <hi>Ahaziah</hi> went to battel, <hi>Athaliah</hi> was left to govern the Kingdome; and her ſon <hi>Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah</hi> being ſlain before his return, ſhe thought the Government ſweet, and could not part with it; and becauſe the Royal ſeed ſtood in her way, ſhe cruelly deſtroyed them, that ſhe might raign with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er freedome. 2. She was earneſt to ſet up a falſe worſhip, even the worſhip of <hi>Baal,</hi> which ſhe thought could not be ſo well done, as by cutting off the Royal race, and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſole power in her hand, that ſhe might do what ſhe pleaſed.</p>
            <p>The buſineſſe you are about this day, is not unlike: You are to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt a young King in the Throne, in a very troubleſome time: and wicked men have riſen up, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped the Kingdome, and put to death the late King moſt unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally. The like motives ſeem to have prevailed with them. 1. Theſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96187:14"/> men by falſhood and diſſimulatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have gotten power in their hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which to them is ſo ſweet, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are unwilling to part with it; A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> becauſe the King and his ſeed ſtoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in their way, they have made awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the King, and diſinherited his chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, that the ſole power might b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in their hand. 2. They have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> number of damnable errors, and falſe worſhip to ſet up, and inten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to take away the Ordinances o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt, and Government of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Kirk. All this cannot be done, un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe they have the ſole power i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their hands, and this they canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have till the King and his poſteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be cut off. But I leave this, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> come to the preſent ſolemnity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> There is a Prince to be inthroned, good <hi>Jehojada</hi> will have the crown put upon his head.</p>
            <p>It may be queſtioned, why they went about this Coronation in a time of ſo great hazard, when <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi> had reigned ſix yeares? Had i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not been better to have defeated <hi>Athaliah,</hi> and then to have crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the King? Two reaſons may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:96187:14"/> rendred, why they delay not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oronation. To crown the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as a duty they were bound to, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>azard ſhould not make them leave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir duty. They did their duty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd left the ſucceſſe to God. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. They crowned the young King, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o endear the peoples affections to their own native Prince, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lienate their hearts from her that had uſurped the Kingdome. If they had delayed, the King being known to be preſerved, it might have brought on, not only comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce with her, but alſo ſubjection to her government, by reſting in it, and being content to lay aſide the righteous heir of the Crown.</p>
            <p>The ſame is obſerved in our Caſe, and many wonder that you ſhould Crown the King in a dangerous time, when the uſurpers have ſuch power in the land, the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may ſerve to anſwer for your doing. 1. It is our neceſſary duty to crown the King upon all ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, and to leave the ſucceſſe to God. 2. It appeareth now, it hath been too long delayed. Delay is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96187:15"/> dangerous, becauſe of the com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ance of ſome, and treachery of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers. If it ſhall be delayed long it is to be feared, that the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> part ſhall ſit down under the ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dow of the <hi>Bramble,</hi> the deſtroyi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> uſurpers.</p>
            <p>I come to the particular han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling of this preſent Text, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeak from it to the preſent ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> I have read the 12. and 17. <hi>v.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cauſe of theſe two which meet t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether, the Crowning of a Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and his renewing the Covena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Amongſt many particulars whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> may be handled from the Text, ſhall confine my ſelf to theſe fiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 1. The Crown, <hi>He put the Cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> upon his head:</hi> 2. The Teſtimon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>He gave them the Teſtimony.</hi> 3. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Anointing, <hi>They Anointed hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Theſe three are in the 12. <hi>verſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> As for that which is ſpoken of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> peoples joy, we ſhall give it a tou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> when we come to the peoples dut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The covenant between God an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the King, and the people, <hi>Jehoja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> made a covenant between God an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the King and the people, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:96187:15"/> ſhould be the Lords people.</hi> 5. The Covenant between the King and the people, <hi>Between the King al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo and the people;</hi> both in the 17. <hi>verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the Crown is put upon his Head. A Crown is the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent badge of Royal Majeſty. To diſcourſe on Crowns in a State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, I ſhall leave unto States-men, and lay only theſe three before you of the Crown.</p>
            <p n="1">I. In putting on of the Crown, it would be well faſtened, for Kings Crowns are often times tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering; and this is a time wherein they totter. There are two things which make Kings Crowns to tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; great ſins, and great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions and troubles; take heed of both.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There are many ſins upon our King and his Family. Sin will make the ſureſt Crown that ever men ſet on to totter. The ſins of former Kings have made this a tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Crown. I ſhall not inſiſt here, ſeeing there hath been a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn day of humiliation through
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96187:16"/> the Land, on Thurſday laſt, for the ſins of the Royal Family. I wiſh the Lord may bleſſe it; and deſire the King may be truly humbled for his own ſins, and the ſins of his fathers houſe, which have been great, beware of putting on theſe ſins with the Crown; For if you put them on, all the well-wiſhers to a King in the three Kingdomes will not be able to hold on the Crown, and keep it from tottering; yea, from falling. Lord, take away the controverſie with the Royal Family, that the Crown may be faſtened ſure upon the Kings head, without falling or tottering.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Troubles and commotions in a Kingdome, make crowns to tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. A Crown at the beſt, and in the moſt calme times, is full of trouble, which if it were well weighed by men, there would not be ſuch hunting after Crowns. I read of a Great man, who conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the trouble and care that accompanied a Crown, ſaid, he would not take it up at his foot, though he might have it for taking.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96187:16"/> Now if a Crown at the beſt be ſo full of troubles, what ſhall one think of a Crown at the worſt, when there are ſo great commotions, wherein the Crown is directly aimed at? Surely it muſt be a tottering crown at the leaſt, eſpecially when for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſins have brought on theſe troubles. As the remedy of the former is true humiliation, and turning unto God; ſo the remedy of the latter, is <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.3. (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Davids</hi> crown) <hi>Thou ſetteſt a crown of pure gold upon his head.</hi> God ſet on <hi>Davids</hi> crown, and therefore it was ſetled, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of many troubles. Men may ſet on crowns, and they may be thrown off again; but when God ſetteth them on, they will be faſt. Enemies have touched the Crown of our King, and caſten it off in the other Kingdome, and have made it totter in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, both the King who is to be crowned, and you who are to crown him, ſhould deal earneſtly with God, to ſet the Crown on the Kings head, and to keep it on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96187:17"/> all the commotions of this generation. 2. A King ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem more of the people he raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth over, than of his crown, Kings uſe to be ſo taken up with their Crowns, that they deſpiſe their people. I would have a King fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Chriſt, the King of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who ſaith of them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.3. <hi>Thou ſhalt be a crown of Glory in the hand of the Lord, and a royal dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dene in the hand of thy God.</hi> Chriſt counteth his people his Crown and Diadem; ſo ſhould a King eſteem the people of the Lord, over whom he ruleth, to be as his Crown and Diadem; take away the people, and a Crown is but an empty ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole. 3. A King when he getteth his Crown on his head, ſhould think at the beſt, it is but a fading Crown. All the Crowns of Kings are but fading Crowns: therefore they ſhould have an eye upon that <hi>Crown of Glory, that fadeth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4. And upon a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that cannot be ſhaken, Heb.</hi> 12.28. that Crown and Kingdome belongeth not to Kings as Kings,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96187:17"/> but unto believers; and a believe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing King hath this Comfort, that <hi>when he hath endured a while, and been tryed, he ſhall receive the crown of life, which the Lord hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to them that love him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. The ſecond thing in this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, is the <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> by this is meant the Law of God; ſo called becauſe it teſtifieth of the mind and will of God. It was command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.18, 19. <hi>when the King ſhall ſit upon the throne of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he ſhall write a copy of the book of the Law, and it ſhall be with him, that he may read therein all the dayes of his life.</hi> The King ſhould have the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> for theſe three main uſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For his information in the way of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.19. This uſe of the Kings having the Book of the Law, is expreſſed, <hi>That he may learn to fear the Lord his God;</hi> the reading of other books may do a King good for Government, but no book will teach him the way of ſalvation, but the book of God. Chriſt biddeth <hi>ſearch the Scriptures,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96187:18"/> for in them ye think to have eternal life, and they teſtifie of me,</hi> Joh. 5.39. He is <hi>a bleſſed man who medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateth in the Law of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 1.1, 2. King <hi>David</hi> was well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted herewith, as appeareth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. Kings ſhould be well exerciſed in Scripture. It is report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of <hi>Alphonſus</hi> King of <hi>Aragon,</hi> that he read the Bible fourteen times, with gloſſes thereupon. I recommend to the King, to take ſome houres for reading holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: It will be a good meanes to make him acquainted with Gods mind, and with Chriſt as a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For this direction in govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Kings read books that may learn them to govern well, which I condemn not, but all the books a King can read, will not make him govern to pleaſe God, as this book. I know nothing that is good in government, but a King may learn it out of the book of God. For this cauſe <hi>Joſhua</hi> is command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.8. <hi>That the book of the law ſhall not depart out of his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96187:18"/> mouth,</hi> and he is commanded <hi>to do according to that is written there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</hi> He ſhould not only do himſelf that which is written in it, but do and govern his people according to that is written in it; King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> knew this uſe of the Teſtimony, who ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.24. <hi>Thy Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies are my delight and my Counſellors.</hi> The beſt counſels that ever a King getteth, are in the book of God; yea the teſtimonies are the beſt and ſureſt Counſellors, becauſe although Kings Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors be never ſo wiſe and truſty, yet they uſe not to be ſo free with a King as they ought: but the Scripture will tell Kings very free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly both their ſin and their duty. 3. For preſervation and cuſtody, the King is <hi>Cuſtos utriuſque tabulae;</hi> the keeper of both tables. Not that he ſhould take upon him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe the Word of God, or to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with it; But that he ſhould preſerve the Word of God, and the true Religion, according to the Word of God, pure, intire, and uncorrupted within his dominions,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96187:19"/> and tranſmit them to poſterity, and alſo be carefull to ſee his ſubjects obſerve both tables, and to puniſh tranſgreſſors of the ſame.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The third thing in this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity is the anointing of the King. The anointing of Kings was not abſolutely neceſſary under the Old Teſtament, for we read not that all the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> were anointed. The <hi>Hebrews</hi> obſerve that anointing of Kings was uſed in three caſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When the firſt of a Family was made King, as <hi>Saul, David.</hi> 2. When there was a queſtion for the Crown, as in the caſe of <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Adoniah.</hi> 3. When there was an interruption of the lawfull ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion by uſurpation, as in the caſe of <hi>Joah,</hi> there is an interruption by the uſurpation of <hi>Athaliah;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is anointed. If this obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation hold, as it is probable, then it was not abſolutely neceſſary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Old Teſtament, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore far leſſe under the New.</p>
            <p>Becauſe it may be ſaid, That in our caſe there is an interruption by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96187:19"/> uſurpation, let it be conſidered; That the Anointing under the Old Teſtament was Typicall, although all Kings were not Types of Chriſt; yet the Anointing of Kings, Prieſts, and Prophets, was typical of Chriſt; and his Offices: but Chriſt being now come, all theſe Ceremonies ceaſe. And therefore the Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Kings, ought not to be uſed in the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, Anointing of Kings hath been in uſe among Chriſtians, not only Papiſts, but Proteſtants, as in the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> and our late King was Anointed with Oyl. It may be replyed, they who uſed it under the New Teſtament took it from the <hi>Jews,</hi> without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. It was moſt in uſe with the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> who to keep Kings and Emperours ſubject to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, did ſwear them to the <hi>Pope,</hi> when they were Anointed, (and yet the Jewiſh Prieſts did never ſwear Kings to themſelves) as for <hi>England</hi> although the <hi>Pope</hi> was caſten off, yet the ſubjection of Kings to Biſhops was ſtill retained, for they Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96187:20"/> the King, and ſware him to the maintenance of their <hi>Prelaticall dignity.</hi> They are here who were witneſſes at the Coronation of the late King. The Biſhops behoved to perform that rite, and the King behoved to be ſworn to them. But now by the bleſſing of God, <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Prelacy</hi> are removed: the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> as limbs of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> are put to the door; let the Anointing of Kings with oyl go to the door with them, and let them never come in again.</p>
            <p>The Anointing with materiall oyle, maketh not a King, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed of the Lord, for he is ſo without it. He is the Anointed of the Lord, who by the divine Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and appointment is a King, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.1. God called <hi>Cyrus</hi> his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed; yet we read not that he was Anointed with oyl. Kings are the Anointed of the Lord, becauſe by the Ordinance of the Lord, their Authority is ſacred and inviolable. It is enough for us to have the thing though we want the Ceremony, which being laid aſide, I will give
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:96187:20"/> ſome Obſervations of the thing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A King being the Lords A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, ſhould be thinking upon a better unction, even that ſpirituall unction, wherewith believers are Anointed, which you have, 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 2.27. <hi>The Anointing ye have received of him abideth in you:</hi> And 2 Cor. 1 21. <hi>He that hath Anointed us, is God who hath alſo ſealed us,</hi> This Anointing is not proper to Kings, but common to believers. Few Kings are ſo Anointed. A King ſhould ſtrive to be a good Chriſtian, and then a good King: The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing with Grace, is better then the Anointing with oyle. It is of more worth for a King to be A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed of the Lord with Grace, then to be the greateſt Monarch of the world without it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Anointing may put a King in mind of the gifts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Kings ſhould be indued, for diſcharge of the Royal calling. For Anointing did ſignifie the gifts of Office. It is ſaid of <hi>Saul,</hi> when he was Anointed King; As 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10 9. <hi>God gave him another heart</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:96187:21"/> And Cap. 11.6. <hi>The ſpirit of God came upon him</hi> it is meant, of a heart for this calling, and a ſpirit of abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity for Government. It ſhould be our deſire this day, that our King may have a ſpirit for his calling, as the ſpirit of Wiſdome, Fortitude, Juſtice, and other Princely indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Anointing may put Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in mind of the Sacret due of the Authority of a King. He ſhould be reſpected, as the Lords Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. There are divers ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that are Enemies to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thory of Kings; As 1. <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> who deny there ſhould be Kings in the New Teſtament. They will have no Kings, nor civil Magiſtrate. 2. The late <hi>Photinians,</hi> who ſpeak reſpectively of Kings, and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, but they take away from them their power, and the exerciſe of it in the adminiſtration of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. 3. Theſe who riſe againſt Kings in open Rebellion, as <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> and <hi>Sheba,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>what have we to do with</hi> David, <hi>the ſon of</hi> Jeſſe? <hi>To your Tents,</hi> O Iſrael 4. They
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96187:21"/> who do not rebel openly, yet they deſpiſe a King in their heart, like the ſons of <hi>Beliall,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. laſt, who ſaid of <hi>Saul</hi> after he was A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed King, <hi>ſhall this man ſave us? And they deſpiſed him, and brought him no preſents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. All theſe meet in our preſent age. 1. <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> who are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the being of Kings are very rife: you may find, to your great grief, a great number of them in that Army that have unjuſtly inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Land, who have trampled upon the Authority of Kings. 2. There are alſo of the ſecond ſort, who are ſecretly <hi>Photinians</hi> in this point, they allow of Kings in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, but they are againſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their power in the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Juſtice. 3. A third ſort in open Rebellion, even all that Generation which are riſen up not only againſt the perſon of the King but Kingly Government. 4. There is a fourth who profeſſe they acknowledge a King, but diſpiſe him in their heart ſaying, <hi>Shall this man ſave us?</hi> I wiſh all had <hi>Davids</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:96187:22"/> tenderneſſe, whoſe <hi>heart ſmote him when he did but cut off the lap of Sauls garment,</hi> that we may be far from cutting off a lap of that juſt power and greatneſſe which God hath allowed to the King, and we have bound our ſelves by Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant not to diminiſh.</p>
            <p>I have gone through the three particulars contained in <hi>ver.</hi> 12. I come to the other two in <hi>v.</hi> 17. which appertain alſo to this ſaid work; for our King is not only to be crowned but to renew a covenant with God and his people, and to make a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the people; Anſwerable hereto there is a twofold covenant in the words, one between God and the King, and the people; God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the one party, the King and the people the other. Another between the King and the people, the King being the one party, the people the other. The covenant with God is the fourth particular propounded to be ſpoken of. The ſum of the covenant ye may find, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23.3. in <hi>Joſiah</hi> his renewing the covenant, <hi>To walk after the Lord, &amp; keep his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:96187:22"/> and teſtimonies with all thy heart, and to perform the words of the covenant.</hi> The renewing of the covenant was after a great defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from God, and the ſetting up of falſe worſhip. The King and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God bound themſelves before the Lord, to ſet up true worſhip, and to aboliſh the falſe. <hi>Scotland</hi> hath a preference in this before other Nations. In time of defection they have renewed a covenant with God to reform all: And becauſe the King after a great defection in that fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is to renew the covenant, I ſhall mention ſome particulars from the League and Covenant.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We are bound to maintain the <hi>true Reformed Religion</hi> in Doctrine Worſhip, Diſcipline and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſtabliſhed in this kingdome, and to endeavour the Reformation of Religion in the other two king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms according to the word of God and the beſt reformed Kirks. By this Article the King is obliged not onely to maintain Religion as it is eſtabliſhed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> but alſo to endeavour the reformation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:96187:23"/> in his other kingdoms: The King ſhould conſider well, when it ſhall pleaſe God to reſtore him to his Government there, that he is bound to endeavour the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the work of Reformation there, as wel as to maintain it here.</p>
            <p>According to the ſecond article, the King is bound without reſpect of perſons to extirpate <hi>Popery, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, Superſtition, Hereſie, Scheiſm &amp; Prophaneſſe,</hi> and whatſoever ſhall be found contrary to ſound Doctrine and the power of godlineſſe; and therefore <hi>Popery</hi> is not to be ſuffred in his Royall family, nor within his Dominions; <hi>Prelacy</hi> once pluck up by the root is not to be permitted to take root again; all <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Error</hi> whatſoever muſt be oppoſed by him to the utmoſt of his power; and by the covenant the <hi>K.</hi> muſt be farre from tolleration of any <hi>falſe Religion</hi> within his Dominions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As the people are bound to maintain the Kings perſon and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the maintenance of the true Religion and liberties of the kingdom: So the King is bound
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:96187:23"/> with them to maintain the rights and priviledges of the Parliament, and liberties of the ſubjects, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the third article.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We are bound to diſcover, and to bring unto condign puniſhment all ſuch as have been or ſhall be <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries, Malignants,</hi> or <hi>evil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments,</hi> in hindring the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion, dividing the king from the people, or one of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms from another, or making any faction or parties amongſt them, hereby the king is bound to have an eye upon ſuch, and neither allow them, nor comply with them, but to concur according to his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to have them cenſured and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, as is expreſſed in the fourth article. I ſhall ſum up all this, That a <hi>K.</hi> entring in covenant with God, ſhould doe as the kings did of old when they entred into covenant, they and their people went on in the work of Reformation, as appears there, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>And all the people of the Lord went to the houſe of Baal, and brake it down, &amp;c.</hi> And godly <hi>Joſiah</hi> when he entred in covenant
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:96187:24"/> made a thorow reformation. There is a fourfold reformation in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and contained in the League and Covenant. 1. A perſonal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. 2. A Family reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 3. A reformation of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories. 4. A reformation of the whole Land: Kings have had their hand in all the Four, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I recommend them to our King.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A perſonal Reformation, A King ſhould reform his own life, that he may be a pattern of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to others, and to this he is tied by the Covenants. The godly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers of <hi>Judah</hi> were pious and religious men. A King ſhould not follow <hi>Machiavell</hi> his counſel, who requireth not that a Prince ſhould be truly religious, but ſaith, that a ſhadow of it, and external ſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are ſufficient: A divelliſh counſel, and it is juſt with God to bring a King to the ſhadow of a Kingdom, who hath but the ſhadow of Religion. We know that diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Kings have been puniſhed of God; and let our King know that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:96187:24"/> no King but a religious king can pleaſe God. <hi>David</hi> is highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for godlineſſe; <hi>Hezekiah</hi> a man eminent for piety, <hi>Joſiah</hi> a young king, commended for the tenderneſſe of his heart when he heard the law of the Lord read; he was much troubled before the Lord when he heard the judgements threatned againſt his Fathers houſe and his people, it is earneſtly wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that our Kings heart may be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and be truly humbled before the Lord for the ſins of his Fathers houſe, and of the land; and for the many evils that are upon that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and upon that Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Family Reformation. The King ſhould reform his Family, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the example of godly kings; <hi>Aſa</hi> when he entred in covenant, ſpared not his Mothers Idolatry. The houſe of our king hath been much defiled by Idolatry. The king is now in covenant, and to renew the covenant, let the Royal Family be reformed; and that it may be a religious Family wherein God will have pleaſure. Let it be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:96187:25"/> not only of Idolatry but of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanity and looſneſs, which hath abounded in it. Much hath been ſpoken of this matter, but little hath been done in it. Let the king and others who have charge in that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily think it lieth upon them as a duty to purge it. And if you would have a Famiy well purged and conſtitute, take <hi>David</hi> for a pattern, in the purgation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of his Pſalm 10. <hi>The fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward heart, wicked perſons, and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers he will have far from him; but his eyes are upon the faithful of the land, that they may dwell with him.</hi> Ye may extent this Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to the Court. A prophane Court is dangerous for a king; it hath been obſerved as a provoking ſin in <hi>England,</hi> which hath drawn down judgement upon King and Court, as appeareth this day. It is to be wiſhed that ſuch were in the Court as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaketh of in that Pſalm. Let the King ſee to it and reſolve with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 101.7. That <hi>he who worketh deceit ſhall not dwell within his houſe; and he who
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:96187:25"/> telleth lies ſhall not tarry in his ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Reformation in Judicatories. It ſhould be carefully ſeen to, that Judicatories be reformed; and that men fearing God, and hating covetouſneſſe, may be placed in them: a King in covenant ſhould do as <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> did, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.5, 6 7. <hi>He ſet Judges in the land, and ſaid, Take heed what you doe: ye judge not for men, but for the Lord, who is with you in judgment: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now let the fear of the Lord be before you,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Reformation of the whole land: the Kings eye ſhould be upon it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.4. <hi>Jehoſhaphat went out through the people, from Beer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba to mount Ephraim, and brought them back to the Lord God of their fathers.</hi> Our land hath great need of reformation; for there is a part of it, that hath ſcarce ever yet found the benefit of it; they are lying without the Goſpel. It will be a work of a covenanted King to have a care that the Goſpel may be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched through the whole land: care alſo would be taken that they who
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:96187:26"/> have the Goſpel may live ſuitably thereto.</p>
            <p>If a king would be a through Reformer, he muſt reformed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, other wayes he will never lay reformation to heart. To make a king a good Reformer, I wiſh him theſe qualifications according to the truth, and in ſincerity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they report <hi>Trajan</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to have been indued. He was 1. Devote at home. 2. Couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in War. 3. Juſt in his Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories. 4. Prudent in all his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. True Piety, Fortitude, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and Prudency are notable qualifications in a Prince, who would reform a kingdome, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form well.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I come now to the fifth and laſt particular, and that is the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venent made between the king and the people. When a king is Crowned, and received by the people, there is a Covenant or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall contract between him and them, containing conditions, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to be obſerved. Time will not ſuffer to inſiſt upon many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:96187:26"/> I ſhall only lay before you three. Firſt, it is clear from this Covenant, That a king hath not abſolute power to do what he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, he is tyed to conditions, by vertue of a Covenant. Secondly, it is clear from this Covenant, that a people are bound to obey their king in the Lord. Thirdly, I ſhall preſent the king with directions, for the Government of the people, who are bound to obey.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is clear, That the kings po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is not abſolute, as kings and flattering Courtiers apprehend, a kings power is a limited power, by this Covenant. And there is a threefold limitation of the kings power.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In regard of ſubordination. There is a power above his, even Gods power, whom he is obliged to obey; and to whom he muſt give an account of his adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Ye heard yeſterday the Text, <hi>By me Kings Raign, Prov.</hi> 8.15. kings have not only their Crowns from God, but they muſt Reign according to his will, which is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:96187:27"/> clear from <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. He is called the Miniſter of God He is but Gods ſervant. I need not ſtay upon this, kings and all others will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this limitation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In regard of Laws, a king is ſworn at his coronation to rule ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſtanding received Laws of the kingdom. The Laws he is ſworn to, limit him that he cannot do againſt them, without a ſinfull breach of this Covenant between the king and the people.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In rgard of government: The totall government is not upon a king. He hath Counſellors, a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Eſtates in the Land, who ſhare in the burden of government. It was never the mind of theſe who receive a king to rule them, to lay all their government upon him, to doe what he pleaſeth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controlement. There is no man able alone to govern all. The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhould not lay that upon one man, who may eaſily miſcarry. The Eſtates of the Land are bound in this contract to bear a burden with him.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:96187:27"/>
            <p>Theſe men who have flattered Kings, to take unto them an abſolute <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower, to do what they pleaſe, have wronged Kings and kingdomes. It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad been good that Kings of late had carried themſelves ſo, as this queſtion of Kings power might never have come in debate; for they have been great looſers thereby, Kings are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deſirous to have things ſpoken and written to hold up their arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and unlimitted power; but that way doth exceedingly wrong them. There is one, a learned man, I confeſſe, who hath written a book for the maintenance of the abſolute power of Kings called <hi>Defenſio Regia</hi> whereby he hath wronged himſelf in his reputation, and the King in his Government. As for the fact of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the life of the late King (whatever was Gods juſtice in it) I do agree with him to condemn it, as a moſt unjuſt and horrid fact, upon their part who did it: But when he cometh to ſpeak to the power of Kings, in giving unto them an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and illimited power, urging the damnahle Maxime, <hi>Quod libet licet,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:96187:28"/> he will have a King to do what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pleaſeth <hi>impune,</hi> and without co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trolement. In this I cannot bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſſent from him.</p>
            <p>In regard of ſubordination, ſome ſay, That a King is countable to none but God: Do what he will, let God take order with it; This lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Kings to <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> let them do what they pleaſe, and take God in their own hand, in regard of Laws, they teach nothing to Kings but Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny: And in regard of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they teach a King to take an arbitrary power himſelf to do what he pleaſeth without controlement. How dangerous this hath been to Kings, is clear by ſad experience. Abuſe of Power and Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, hath been one of Gods great controverſies, with our kings and Predeceſſors; God in his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, becauſe power hath been abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, hath thrown it out of their hands. And I may confidently ſay, that Gods controverſie with the kings of the Earth, is for their Arbitrary and Tyrannical Government.</p>
            <p>It is good for our king to learn to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:96187:28"/> be wiſe in time; and know, that he receiveth this day a power to govern; but a power limited by contract; and theſe conditions he is bound by Oath to ſtand to. Kings are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, who think that the people are ordained for the king; and not the king for the people. The Scripture ſheweth the contrary, <hi>Romans</hi> 13.4. The king is the Miniſter of God, for the Peopes good. God will not have a king in an arbitrary way, to encroach upon the poſſeſſions of Subjects <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 45.7.8. <hi>A portion is appointed for the Prince.</hi> And it is ſaid, <hi>My Princes ſhall no more oppreſſe my people; and the reſt of the Land ſhall he give unto the Houſe of Iſrael, according to their Tribes.</hi> The king hath his diſtinct poſſeſſions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues from the peoples; he muſt not oppreſs and do what he pleaſeth, there muſt be no Tyranny upon the Throne.</p>
            <p>I deſire not to ſpeak much of this Subject. Men have been very ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in medling with the power of kings; yet ſeeing theſe dayes have brought forth debates concerning the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:96187:29"/> power of kings, it will be neceſſary to be clear in the matter. Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities ſhould be ſhunned. A king ſhould keep within the bounds of the Covenant made with the people, in the exerciſe of his power: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the laſt, I ſhall propound theſe three to your conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A king abuſing his power, to the overthrow of Religion, Laws and Liberties, which are the very funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentalls of this contract and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, may be controled and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and if he ſet himſelf to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw all theſe by Arms, then they who have power, as the Eſtates of a Land, may and ought to reſiſt by Arms; Becauſe he doth, by that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, break the very bonds, and overthrow the eſſentials of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and Covenant. This may ſerve to juſtifie the proceedings of this kingdome againſt the late king, who in an hoſtile way ſet himſelf to overthrow Religion, Parliaments, Laws and Liberties.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Every breach of Covenant wherein a king faileth, after he hath entred in Covenant, doth not diſſolve
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:96187:29"/> the bond of the Covenant. Neither ſhould Subjects lay aſide a king for every breach, except the breaches be ſuch as overthrow the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of the Covenant with the people. Many examples of this may be brought from Scripture. I ſhall give but one. King <hi>Aſa</hi> entered ſolemnly in Covenant with God and his People, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. After that he falleth in groſs tranſgreſſions and breaches, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. He aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates himſelf and entered in League with <hi>Benhadad</hi> king of <hi>Syria,</hi> an <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later,</hi> he impriſoned <hi>Hanani</hi> the Lords Prophet, who reproved him, and threatned judgement againſt that aſſociation; and at the ſame time he oppreſſed ſome of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and yet, for all this, they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lay aſide, nor count him an Hypocrite.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Private perſons ſhould be very circumſpect about that which they do in relation to the Authority of kings. It is very dangerous for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men to meddle with the power of kings, and the ſuſpending of them from the exerciſe thereof. I do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:96187:30"/> confeſs, that I find no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of it: The Prophets taught not ſuch doctrine to their people, nor the Apoſtles nor the reformed kirks. Have ever private men, Paſtours, or Profeſſors, given into the Eſtates of a Land, as their judgement, unto which they reſolved to adhere, That a king ſhould be ſuſpended from the exerciſe of his power? And if we look upon thoſe Godly Paſtours who lived in king <hi>James</hi> his time, of whom one may truly ſay, more faithful men lived not in theſe laſt times: For they ſpared not to tell the king his faults to his face: Yea, ſome of them ſuffered perſecution for their honeſty and freedom; Yet we never read, nor have heard, that any of thoſe godly Paſtours joyned with other private men, did never remonſtrate to Parliament or Eſtate, as their judgement, that the king ſhould be ſuſpended from the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of his Royal power.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is clear from this Covenant, that people ſhould obey their King in the Lord: for as the king is bound by Covenant to make uſe of his power
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:96187:30"/> to their good: ſo are they bound to obey him in the Lord in the exerciſe of that power. About the peoples duty to their King take theſe four Obſervations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the obedience of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is in ſubordination to God; For the Covenant is firſt with God, and then with the King. If a King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand any thing contrary to the will of God, in this caſe <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is better to obey God then man.</hi> There is a line drawn from God to the people they are loweſt in the line, and have Magiſtrates ſuperiour and ſupreme above them, and God above all. When the King commandeth the people that which is lawful and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by God, then he ſhould be obeyed, becauſe he ſtandeth in the right line under God, who hath put him in his place. But if he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that which is unlawful, and forbidden of God, in that he ſhall not be obeyed to do it; becauſe he is out of his line. That a King is to be obeyed with this ſubordination, is evident from Scripture; take one place for all, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:96187:31"/> ye have both obedience urged to Superiour Powers at the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, and damnation threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt thoſe who reſiſt the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full power.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid by ſome, that many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in <hi>Scotland</hi> will not have King <hi>Jeſus,</hi> but King <hi>Charles</hi> to reign. Faithful men are wronged by ſuch ſpeeches. I do not underſtand theſe men. For if they think that a King and <hi>Jeſus</hi> are inconſiſtent; then they will have no King. But I ſhall be far from entertaining ſuch thoughts of them. If they think the doing of a neceſſary duty for King <hi>Charles</hi> is to prefer his Intereſt to Chriſts, this alſo is an errour. Honeſt Miniſters can very well diſcern between the intereſt of Chriſt and of the King. I know no Miniſters that ſetting up King <hi>Charles</hi> with prejudice to Chriſts in ereſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third particular about this Covenant reſteth to be ſpoken of, to wit, ſome directions to the King, for the right performing of his Duty, whereof I ſhall give ſeven.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A King, meeting with many
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:96187:31"/> difficulties in doing of duty, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſtrong corruption within, and many tentations without; he ſhould be careful to ſeek GOD by Prayer for grace to overcome theſe Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and for an underſtanding heart to Govern his people. <hi>Solomon</hi> having in his option to ask what he would, he asked an Underſtanding Heart, to go out and in before his people: knowing that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a people was a very difficile work, and needed more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary underſtanding. A King alſo hath many enemies (as our King hath this day) and a Praying King is a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing King. <hi>Aſa</hi> when he had to do with a mighty enemy, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14. prayed fervently and prevailed. <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> was invaded with a mighty enemy, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. He prayed and did prevail. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> prayed againſt <hi>Senucherib</hi>'s huge Army and prevailed, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>Sir, you have many difficulties and oppoſitions to meet with; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint your ſelf with Prayer; be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant with GOD, and he will fight for You. Prayers are not in much
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:96187:32"/> requeſt at Court; but a Covenanted King muſt bring them in requeſt. I know a King is burthened with mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity of affairs, and will meet with many diverſions: But, Sir, you muſt not be diverted; and take hours and ſet them apart for that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe; men being once acquainted with your way way, will not dare to divert you. Prayer to God will make your affairs eaſie all the day. I read of a king of whom his Courtiers ſaid, He ſpoke oftner with God, then with men. If you be frequent in Prayer you may expect the bleſſing of the moſt high upon your ſelf, and your Government.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A king muſt be carefull of the kingdom which he hath ſworn to maintain We have had many of too private a ſpirit, by whom ſelf-intereſt hath been preferred to the publick. It becommeth a king well to be of a publick ſpirit, to care more for the publick then his own intereſt. Senates and States have had Motto's written over the doors of the Meeting-places; Over the Senates houſe at <hi>Rome</hi> was written, <hi>Ne quid Republica detrimenti
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:96187:32"/> capiat;</hi> I ſhall wiſh this may be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten over your Aſſembly-houſes: But there is another which I would have written with it, <hi>Ne quid Eccleſia detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti capiat.</hi> Be carefull of both; let not kirk nor State ſuffer hurt; let them go together. The beſt way for ſtanding of a kingdome, is a well conſtitute kirk: They deceive kings who make them believe that the Government of the kirk, I mean Presbyterial Government, cannot ſute with Monarchy. They ſute well, it being the Ordinance of Chriſt, rendring to God what is Gods, and to <hi>Caeſar</hi> what is <hi>Caeſars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, kings who have a tender care of the kirk, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.3. are called Nurſing Fathers. You would be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that the Goſpel may have free paſſage through the kingdome, and that the Government of the kirk may be preſerved intire, according to your Solemn Engagement. The kirk hath met with many enemies, as <hi>Papiſts, Prelates, Malignants,</hi> which I paſſe as known enemies. But there are two ſorts more, who at this time would be carefully looked on.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:96187:33"/>1. <hi>Sectaries,</hi> great enemies to the kirk, and to all the Ordinances of Chriſt, and more particularly to <hi>Presbyterian Government,</hi> which they have and would have altogether deſtroyed. A king ſhould ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt theſe, becauſe they are enemies as well to the king as to the kirk, and ſtrive to make both fall together.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Eraſtians,</hi> more dangerous ſnares to kings, than <hi>Sectaries;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe kings can look well enough to theſe, who are againſt themſelves and their power, as <hi>Sectaries,</hi> who will have no king: But <hi>Eraſtians</hi> give more power to kings than they ſhould have, and are great enemies to Presbyterial Government: For they would make kings believe that there is no Government but the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and derived from thence; which is a great wrong to the Son of God, who hath the Government of the kirk diſtinct from the Civil, yet no wayes prejudicial to it, being ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, and of another nature. Chriſt did put the Magiſtrate out of ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that his kingdom was prejudicial
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:96187:33"/> to Civil Government, affirming, <hi>My Kingdom is not of this world.</hi> This Government Chriſt hath not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to kings, but to the Office-bearers of his houſe; who in regard of civil ſubjection, are under the civil power as well as others; but in their ſpiritual adminiſtration they are under Chriſt, who hath not given to any king upon earth, the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of ſpiritual things to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SIR,</hi> You are in covenant with God and his people, and are obliged to maintain <hi>Presbyterial Government,</hi> as well againſt <hi>Eraſtians</hi> as <hi>Sectaries.</hi> I know this <hi>Eraſtian</hi> humour aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth at Court. It may be ſome en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make your reproach up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that, for which God hath puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your Predeceſſors. Be who he will that medleth with this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to overturn it, it ſhall be as heavy to him as the burthenſome ſtone to the enemies of the kirk, <hi>They are cut in pieces who burthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with it,</hi> Zach. 12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A <hi>King</hi> in Covenant with the people of God, ſhould make much
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:96187:34"/> of thoſe who are in Covenant with him; having in high eſtimation the faithful Servants of Chriſt, and the godly people of the Land. It is rare to find kings lovers of faithful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and pious people. It hath been the fault of our own Kings to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the godly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let the <hi>King</hi> love the Servant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſt, who ſpeak the truth. Evi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Kings are branded with this, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they contemned the Prophets, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25. when <hi>Amaziah</hi> had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the gods of <hi>Seir,</hi> and ſet them up for his gods, a Prophet came to him and reproved him, unto whom the <hi>King</hi> ſaid, <hi>Who made thee of the King counſel, forbear leſt thou be ſmitten</hi> This contempt of the Prophets warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is a fore-runner of following deſtruction. Be a careful hearer o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gods Word; take with reproof, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of it as <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141.5. <hi>An excellent oyl which ſhall not brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the head.</hi> To make much of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants of Chriſt, will be an evidence of reality.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let the <hi>King</hi> eſteem well o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> godly Profeſſors. Let Piety be in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:96187:34"/> It is a fault very common, that pious men, becauſe of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious and ſtrict walking, are ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Prophane,</hi> who love to live looſely. It is uſual with <hi>prophane men</hi> to labour to bring kings unto a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſte of the godly; eſpecially when men who have profeſſed Piety be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſcandalous; whereupon they are ready to judge all pious men to be like them, and take occaſion to ſpeak evil of Piety. I fear at this time when men who have been commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Piety, have fallen fouly, and betrayed their truſt; that men will take advantage to ſpeak againſt the godly of the Land. Beware of this, for its <hi>Satans</hi> policy to put piety out of requeſt. Let not this move any, Fall who will, Piety is ſtill the ſame, and pious men will make conſcience both of their wayes and truſt. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, they are precious in Gods eyes, who will not ſuffer men to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe them, without their reward. Sir, let not your heart be from the godly in the Land, whatever hath fain out at this time. I dare affirm that there are very many really
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:96187:35"/> godly men, who by their prayers are ſupporting your Throne.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A king ſhould be carefull whom he putteth in places of truſt, as a main thing for the good of the kingdome. It is a Maxime that Truſt ſhould not be put in their hands who have oppreſſed the people, or have betrayed their truſt. There is a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in ſtory, meet for this purpoſe. One <hi>Septimius Arabmus,</hi> a man fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous or rather infamous for Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion was put out of the Senate but re-admitted. About this time <hi>Alexander Severus</hi> being choſen to the Empire, the Senators did enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him with publick ſalutations and congratulations, <hi>Severus</hi> eſpying <hi>Arabinus,</hi> amongſt the Senators, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>O Numina! Arabinus non ſolum vivit, ſed in Senatum venit. Ah! Arabinus</hi> not onely liveth, but he is in the Senate. Out of juſt indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he could not endure to ſee him As all are not meet for places of truſt in Judicatures, ſo all are not meet for places of truſt in Armies. Men would be choſen who are godly and able for the charge.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:96187:35"/>
            <p>But there are ſome who are not meet for truſt. 1. They who are godly, but have no skil nor ability for the place; a man may be a truly godly man, who is not fit for ſuch a place, and no wrong is done to him, nor to godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when the place is denied to him. I wonder how a godly man can take upon him a place whereof he hath no skill. 2. They who have neither skill nor courage are very unmeet, for if it be a place of never ſo great moment, faint-heartedneſs wil make them quit it. 3. They who are both skilfull and ſtout, yet are not honeſt, but perſidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and treacherous ſhould have no truſt at all.</p>
            <p>Of all theſe we have ſad experience which ſhould not move you to make choice of prophane, and godleſs men, by whom a bleſſing is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, but it ſhould move you to be wary in your choice, I am confident ſuch may be had, who will be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for religion, king and kingdome.</p>
            <p>There hath been much debate about the exerciſe of the kings pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, yet he is put in the exerciſe of his power, and this day put in a better
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:96187:36"/> capacity to exerciſe it by his Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Many are affraid that the exerciſe of his power, ſhall prove dangerous to the cauſe, and indeed I confeſſe there is a ground of fear, when we conſider how this power hath been abuſed by former Kings therefore Sir, make good uſe of your power, and ſee that you rather keep within bounds, then exceed in the exerciſe of it. I may very well give ſuch a counſel, as an old Counſellour gave to a king of <hi>France.</hi> He ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpent many years at Court, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to retire into the Country for enjoying privacy fit for his age; and having obtained leave, the King his Maſter required him to ſet down and write ſome advice of Government, to leave behind him, which he out of Modeſty declined. The King would not be denyed, but left with him Pen and Ink, and a ſheet paper. He being alone after ſome thoughts, wrote with fair and legible Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters in the head of the ſheet, <hi>Modus,</hi> in the middle of the ſheet, <hi>Modus,</hi> and in the foot of the ſheet, <hi>Modus,</hi> and wrote no more in all his paper
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:96187:36"/> which he wrapped up and delivered to the King, meaning that the beſt counſel he could give him, was, that he ſhould keep temper in all things. Nothing more fit for a young King, then to keep temper in all. Take his Counſell Sir, and be mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rate in the uſe of your power. The beſt way to keep power is moderation in the uſe of it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The King hath many Enemies, even ſuch as are enemies to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and to all Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and are now in the bowells of this kingdome waſting and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: beſtir your ſelf according to Vows and Oaths that are upon you, to be active for the relief of Chriſts kingdome born down by them in all the three kingdomes; and for the relief of this kingdome grievouſly oppreſſed by them. We ſhall ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire, that God would put that ſpirit upon our King, now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered upon publick Government, which he hath put upon the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of his people from their cruell oppreſſors.</p>
            <p>In ſpeaking of the Kings behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:96187:37"/> to Enemies. One thing I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not paſſe. There is much ſpoken of a Treaty with his Enemy, I am not of the judgement of ſome, who diſtinguiſh a Treaty before invaſion, and after invaſion, and ſay, treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is very lawfull before invaſion; becauſe it is ſuppoſed there is little wrong done; but after invaſion when a kingdome is wronged, and put to infinite loſſes, then ſay a Treaty is to be ſhunned: but in my judgement a Treaty may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full after invaſion, and wrongs ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteined. The end of war is peace, neither ſhould deſire of revenge ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct it, providing it be ſuch a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Peace, as is not prejudiciall to Religion nor to the ſafety of the Kingdome, nor to the undoubted right of the King, nor the League and Covenant whereunto we are ſolemnly engaged.</p>
            <p>But I muſt break off this Treaty with a ſtory related in <hi>Plutarch.</hi> The City of <hi>Athens</hi> was in a great ſtrait, wherein they knew not what to do. <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> in this ſtrait ſaid, he had ſomething wherein to give his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:96187:37"/> for the behoof of the State; but he thought it not fit to deliver himſelf publickly: <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> a man of great truſt, is appointed to hear him privately, and to make an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count as he thought meet. When <hi>Ariſtides</hi> came to make his report to the Senate, he told them that <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtocles</hi> his advice was indeed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, but not honeſt: Whereupon the people would not ſo much as hear it. There is much whiſpering of a Treaty, they are not willing to ſpeak publickly of it. Hear them in private, and it may be the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ſhall be profitable, but not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. If a Treaty ſhould be, let it be both profitable and honeſt, and no lover of peace will be againſt it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Seeing the King is now upon renewing of the Covenants, it would be remembred, that we enter into Covenant, according to our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion therein, with reality, ſincerity, and conſtancy, which are the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of good Covenanters. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doubt of your reality in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant: Let your ſincerity and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality be evidenced by your ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:96187:38"/> and conſtancy; for many have begun well, but have not been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</p>
            <p>In the ſacred Hiſtory of Kings, we find a note put upon Kings accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their carriages. One of three ſentences written upon them. 1. Some Kings have this written on them, <hi>He did evil in the ſight of the Lord.</hi> They neither begin well, nor end well. Such an one was <hi>Ahaz</hi> King of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> and divers others in that Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. 2. Others have this written on them, <hi>He did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord, but not with a perfect heart.</hi> Such a one was <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.2. He was neither ſincere nor conſtant: when God bleſſed him with victory againſt the <hi>Edomites,</hi> he ſell fouly from the true worſhip of God, and ſet up the gods of Edom. 3. A third ſentence is written upon the godly Kings of <hi>Judah, He did right in the ſight of the Lord, with a perfect heart;</hi> as <hi>Aſa, Hezekiah, Jehoſaphat</hi> and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah.</hi> They were both ſincere and conſtant. Let us neither have the firſt nor the ſecond, but the third
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:96187:38"/> written upon our King, <hi>He did right in the ſight of the Lord, with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect heart.</hi> Begin well, and continue conſtant.</p>
            <p>Before I cloſe, I ſhall ſeek leave to lay before our young King two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, to beware of; and one to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, the two warning examples one of them is in my text, another in our own Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>The firſt example of <hi>Joaſh,</hi> he began well, and went on in godly Reformation all the dayes of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hojada;</hi> but it is obſerved 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.17. after the dayes of <hi>Jehojada,</hi> the Princes of <hi>Judah</hi> came, and did obeyſance to the King, and he hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened unto them, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth they had been at wait till the death of <hi>Jehojada;</hi> and took that opportunity to deſtroy the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and ſet up falſe worſhip, flattering the King to that effect: For it is ſaid, <hi>They left the houſe of the Lord, and ſerved groves and Idols,</hi> and were ſo far from being reclaimed by the Prophet of the Lord, that was ſent unto them, that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt <hi>Zechariah</hi> the ſon of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:96187:39"/> 
               <hi>Jehojada,</hi> who reproved them mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and ſtoned him with ſtones, and flew him at the Kings commandment. And <hi>ver.</hi> 22. it is ſaid, <hi>Joaſh remembred not the kindneſſe that Jehojada his Father had done to him, but ſlew his Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Take this example for a warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: You are obliged by the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to go on in the work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, it may be ſome great ones are waiting their time, not having opportunity to work for the preſent, till afterward they may make obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance, and perſwade you to deſtroy all that hath been done in the work of God theſe divers years. Beware of it, Let no allurement of perſwaſion prevail with you to fall from that, which this day you bind your ſelf to maintain.</p>
            <p>Another example I give you, yet in recent memory, of your Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father King <hi>James.</hi> He fell to be King very young, in a time full of difficulties; yet there was a godly party in the Land, who did put the Crown upon his head. And when
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:96187:39"/> he came to ſome years, He and and his people entred in a Covenant with God, he was much commended by godly and faithful men, comparing him to young <hi>Joſiah</hi> ſtanding at the Altar, renewing a Covenant with God; and he himſelf did thank God that he was born in a reformed Kirk, better reformed then <hi>England;</hi> for they retained many Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh ceremonies: yea, better reformed then <hi>Geneva;</hi> for they keep ſome holy days: charging his people to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and promiſing himſelf to continue in that Reformation, and to maintain the ſame. Notwithſtanding of all this, he made a foul defection: He remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred not the kindneſs of them who had held the Crown upon his head; yea, he perſecuted faithful Miniſters, for oppoſing that courſe of defection. He never reſted till he had undone Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Government, and Kirk Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, ſetting up Biſhops, and bringing in ceremonies, againſt which he had formerly given large teſtimonies. In a word, he laid the foundation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon his Son our late King did build much miſchief in Religion all the days of his life.</p>
            <p>Sir, I lay this example before you
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:96187:40"/> the rather, becauſe it is ſo near you, that the guiltineſſe of the tranſgreſſion lieth upon the Throne and Family, and it is one of the ſins for which you have profeſſed humiliation very lately. Let it be laid to heart, take warning, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite not faithful mens kindneſſe with perſecution; yea, requite not the Lord ſo, who hath preſerved you to this time, and is ſetting a Crown upon your head. Requite not the Lord with apoſtaſie and defection from a ſworn Covenant, but be ſtedfaſt in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, as you would give teſtimony of your true humiliation for the defection of thoſe that went before you.</p>
            <p>I have ſet theſe two examples before you as Beacons to warn you to keep off ſuch dangerous courſes, and ſhall add one of that godly mans adherence to God. The example is of <hi>Hezekiah, who did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord,</hi> 2 Kings 18.6, 6. <hi>It is ſaid of him, he truſted in the Lord God of Iſrael, and he clave unto the Lord, and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not from following him, but kept his Commandments.</hi> And ver. 7. <hi>The Lord was with him, and he proſpered whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he went forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, follow this example, cleave unto
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:96187:40"/> the Lord, and depart not from follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and the Lord will be with you, and proſper you whitherſoever you go. To this Lord, from whom we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a bleſſing on this dayes work, be glory and praiſe for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sermon being ended, Prayer was made for a bleſſing upon the Doctrine delivered.</p>
            <p>The King being to renew the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants firſt the National Covenant, then the ſolemn League and Covenant were diſtinctly read.</p>
            <p>After the reading of theſe Covenants the Miniſter prayed for grace to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the contents of the Covenants, and for faithful ſtedfaſtneſs in the Oath of God; and then (the Miniſters, and Commiſſioners of the General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, deſired to be preſent, ſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Pulpit) he miniſted the Oath unto the King who kneeling, and lifting up his right hand, did ſwear in the words following.</p>
            <p>I CHARLES <hi>King of Great</hi> Brittain, France, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>do aſſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare by ſolemn Oath, in the preſence of Almighty God, the Searcher of hearts, my allowance and approbation of the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:96187:41"/> National Covenant, and of the ſolemn League and Covenant above written, and faithfully obliege my ſelf, to proſecute the ends thereof in my Station and Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; And that I for my ſelf and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, ſhall conſent and agree to all Acts of Parliament enjoyning the Nationall Covenant, and of the Solemne League and Covenant, and fully eſtabliſh Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall Government, the Directory of Worſhip, Confeſſion of Faith, and Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſms in the Kingdome of</hi> Scotland, <hi>as they are approved by the Generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of this Kirk and Parliament of this Kingdome: And that I ſhall give my Royall aſſent to Acts and Ordinances of Parliament paſſed or to be paſſed, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning the ſame in my other Dominions: And that I ſhall obſerve theſe in my own practiſe and Family, and ſhall never make oppoſiton to any of theſe, or endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour any change thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the King had thus ſolemnly ſworn the Nationall Covenant, the League and Covenant, and the Kings Oath ſubjoyned unto both being drawn up into a fair Partchment; the King did ſubſcribe the ſame in preſence of all.</p>
            <p>Thereafter the King aſcendeth the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:96187:41"/> Stage, and ſitteth down in the Chair of State.</p>
            <p>Then the Lords, great Conſtable, and Marſhall, went to the four corners of the Stage with the Lyon going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; who ſpoke to the people theſe words; Sirs, <hi>I do preſent unto you the King,</hi> Charles, <hi>the rightfull and undoubted Heir of the Crown and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of this Realm; this day is by the Parliament of this Kingdome appointed for his Coronation. And are you not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to have him for your King, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Subjects to his Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which action, the Kings Majeſty ſtood up, ſhowing himſelf to the people in each corner, And the penple expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their willingneſſe, by chearful ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, in theſe words, <hi>God ſave the King, Charles the Second.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thereafter the Kings Majeſty ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Conſtable and Marſhall, cometh down from the Stage, and ſitteth down in the Chair, where he heard the Sermon.</p>
            <p>The Miniſter, accompanied with the Miniſters before mentioned, cometh from the Pulpit toward the King; and requireth, If he was willing to take the Oath, appointed to be taken at the Coronation.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:96187:42"/>
            <p>The King anſwered, he was moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <p>Then the Oath of Coronation, as it contained in the eighth Act of the firſt Parliament of King <hi>James,</hi> being read by the Lyon, the Tenour whereof fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe, that the increaſe of Vertue, and ſuppreſſing of Idolatry, craveth, That the Prince and the people be of one perfect Religion, which of Gods mercy is now preſently profeſſed within this Realm: Therefore it is ſtatuted and ordained, by our Soveraign Lord, my Lord Regent, and three eſtates of this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: that all Kings, Princes, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates whatſoever, holding their place which hereafter at any time ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to Raign, and bear rule over this Realm, at the time of their Coronation, and receipt of their Princely Authority, make their faithful promiſe in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the eternal God: That enduring the whole courſe of their lives, they ſhall ſerve the ſame Eternal God, to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of their power, according as he hath required in his moſt holy Word, revealed and contained in the New and Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments; And according to the ſame Word, ſhall maintain the true Religion
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:96187:42"/> of Chriſt Jeſus, the preaching of his Holy Word, and due and right Miniſtration of the Sacraments now received, and preached within this Realm. And ſhall aboliſh and gainſtand all falſe religions, contrary to the ſame: and ſhall rule the people committed to their charge, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will and command of God revealed in his foreſaid Word, and according to the Loveable Lawes, and Conſtitutions received in this Realm, no wayes repugnant to the ſaid Word of the Eternall God, And ſhall procure to the uttermoſt of their power, to the Kirk of God and whole Chriſtian people, true and perfect peace, in time coming. The right, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ents, with all juſt priviledges of the Crown of</hi> Scotland, <hi>to preſerve and keep inviolated: Neither ſhall they transfer, nor alienate the ſame. They ſhall forbid and repreſse in all Eſtates, and degrees, reaf, oppreſſion, and all kind of wrong; In all judgements they ſhall command and procure that juſtice, and equity be kept to all creatures, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, as the Lord and Father of Mercies, be mercifull unto them: and out of their Lands and Empire they ſhall be careful to root out all Hereticks, and enemies to the true worſhip of God, that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:96187:43"/> ſhall be convict by the true Kirk of God, of the aforeſaid crimes; and that they ſhall faithfully affirm the things above written, by their Solemn Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Miniſter tendered the Oath unto the King, who kneeling, and holding up his right hand, ſwore in theſe words. <hi>By the Eternall and Almighty God, who liveth and reigneth for ever, I ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and keep all that is contained in this Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This done the Kings Majeſty ſitteth down in his Chair, and repoſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a little.</p>
            <p>Then the King ariſeth from his chair, and is diſ-robed by the Lord great Chamberlain, of the Princely robe, wherewith he entred the Kirk, and is inveſted by the ſaid Chamberlain in his Royal Robes.</p>
            <p>Thereafter, the King being brought to the Chair on the North ſide of the Kirk, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pported as formerly, the Sword was brought by Sir <hi>William Cockburn</hi> of <hi>Langtown,</hi> Gentleman uſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, from the table, and delivered to the Lyon King of Armes, who giveth it to the Lord great Conſtable, who putteth the ſame in the Kings hand, ſaying, Sir, <hi>Receive this Kingly Sword, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:96187:43"/> of the Faith of Chriſt, and protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Kirk, and of the true Religion, as it is preſently profeſſed within this Kingdome, and according to the Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Covenant, and League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and for executing Equity and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and for puniſhment of all iniquity and injuſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This done, the great Conſtable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth the Sword from the King, and girdeth the ſame about his ſide.</p>
            <p>Thereafter the King ſitteth down in his Chair; and then the Spurs were put on him by the Earl Marſhal.</p>
            <p>Thereafter, <hi>Archibald</hi> Marquis of <hi>Argyle</hi> having taken the Crown in his hands, the Miniſter prayed to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Lord would purge the Crown from the ſins and tranſgreſſions of them that did reign before him: That it might be a pure Crown; That God would ſettle the Crown upon the kings head: and ſince men that ſet it on, were not able to ſettle it, that the Lord would put it on, and preſerve it.</hi> And then the ſaid Marquis put the Crown on the Kings head.</p>
            <p>Which done, Lyon King of Armes, the great Conſtable ſtanding b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:96187:44"/> cauſeth an Herauld to call the whole Noble men, one by one, according to their ranks; who coming before the King, kneeling, and with their hand touching the Crown on the Kings head, ſwore theſe words; <hi>By the Eternal and Almighty God, who liveth and reigneth for ever, I ſhall ſupport thee to my utmoſt.</hi> And when they had done, then all the Nobility held up their hands, and <hi>ſware to be loyal and true ſubjects, and true to the Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Earl Marſhal, with the Lyon, going to the four corners of the Stage, the Lyon proclaimeth the Obligatory Oath of the people. And the people holding up their hands all the time, did ſwear, <hi>By the Eternal and Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, who liveth and reigneth for ever, we become your liege men, and Truth and Faith ſhall bear unto you, and live and dye with you, againſt all manner of folks whatſoever, in your ſervice, according to the National Covenant, and ſolemne League and Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then did the Earles and Vicounts put on their Crowns, and the Lyon like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe put on his.</p>
            <p>Then did the Lord Chamberlain looſe the Sword wherewith the King
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:96187:44"/> was girded, and drew it; and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it drawn into the Kings hands, and the King put it into the hands of the great Conſtable, to carry it naked before him.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>John</hi> Earl of <hi>Crawford</hi> and <hi>Lindeſay</hi> took the Scepter and put it in the Kings right hand, ſaying, <hi>Sir, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this Scepter, the ſign of Royal power of the Kingdome, that you may govern your ſelf right, and defend all the Chriſtian people committed by God to your charge, puniſhing the wicked, and protecting the juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then did the King aſcend the Stage, attended by the Officers of the Crown, and Nobility, and was inſtalled in the Royal Throne by <hi>Archibald</hi> Marquis of <hi>Argyle,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Stand, and hold faſt from henceforth, the place whereof you are the lawful and righteous heir, by a long and lineal ſucceſſion of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which is now delivered unto you by authority of Almighty God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the King was ſet down upon the Throne, the Miniſter ſpoke to him a word of Exhortation, as followeth.</p>
            <p>Sir, <hi>You are ſet down upon the throne in a very difficil time: I ſhall therefore put you in mind of a Scriptural expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:96187:45"/> of a Throne,</hi> 1 Chron. 29.23. <hi>It is ſaid,</hi> Solomon ſate on the Throne of the Lord. <hi>Sir, you are a King and a King in Covenant with the Lord, if You would have the Lord to own you to be his king, and his Torone to be your Throne, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you may have ſome thoughts of this expreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>It is the Lords Throne; Remember you have a King above you, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth Thrones: He ſetteth kings and Thrones, and dethroneth them at his pleaſure: Therefore take a word of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; be thankful to him, who hath brought you through many wanderings to ſet you on this Throne: kiſſe the ſon leſt he be angry, and learn to ſerve him with fear, who is terrible to the kings of the earth.</hi> 2. <hi>Your throne is the Lords throne, and your people the Lords people; Let not your heart be lifted up above your brethren,</hi> Deut. 17.20. <hi>They are your brethren, not only fleſh of your fleſh, but brethren by Covenant with God; let your Government be refreſhing unto them, as the rain on the mowen graſſe.</hi> 3. <hi>Your Throne is the Lords Throne; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of making his Throne a Throne of iniquity: There is ſuch a throne,</hi> Pſal.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:96187:45"/> 94.20. Which frameth miſchief by Law; <hi>God will not own ſuch a throne, it hath no fellowſhip with him.</hi> Sir, <hi>there is too much iniquity upon the throne by your predeceſſors, who framed miſchief by a Law; ſuch lawes as have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Religion, and grievous to the Lords people: You are on the Throne, and have the Scepter, beware of touching miſchievous laws therewith. But as the Throne is the Lords Throne, let the lawes be the Lords lawes, agreeable to his Word, ſuch as are terrible to evil doers, and comfortable to the godly, and a relief to the poor and oppreſſed in the Land.</hi> 4. <hi>The Lords Throne putteth you in mind whom you ſhall have about the throne; wicked Counſellors are not for a King upon the Lords Throne:</hi> Solomon <hi>knew this, who ſaid,</hi> Prov. 25.5. Take away the wicked from before the King, and his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. <hi>And</hi> Prov. 20.8. A King upon the Throne ſcattereth away all evil with his eyes. 5 <hi>The Lords throne putteth you in mind, that the judgement on the throne ſhould be the Lords. Take the exhortation</hi> Jer. 22. <hi>from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the Prophet hath a command to go to the houſe of the King of Judah, and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:96187:46"/> ſay, Hear the word of the Lord, O King of Judah, that ſitteth upon the Throne, &amp; thy ſervants, and thy people, execute ye judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and righteouſneſſe, and deliver the ſpoil out of the hand of the oppreſſour: and do no wrong, do no violence to the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the fatherleſſe, nor the widow, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhed innocent bloud in this place. If ye do this thing indeed, then ſhall there enter by the gates of this houſe, Kings ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon the throne of</hi> David. <hi>But if ye will not hear theſe words, I ſwear by my ſelf, ſaith the Lord, this houſe ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a deſolation. And</hi> ver. 7. <hi>I will prepare deſtroyers againſt thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, Deſtroyers are prepared for the injuſtice of the Throne, I intreat you execute righteous judgment; if you do it not, your houſe will be a deſolation: But if you do that which is right, God ſhall remove the deſtroyers, and you ſhall be eſtabliſhed on your Throne: and there ſhall yet be Dignity in your houſe, for your ſervants and for your people.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If your Throne be the Throne of the Lord take a word of encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt Throne-adverſaries. Your enemies are the enemies of the Lords Throne: Make your peace with God
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:96187:46"/> in Chriſt, and the Lord ſhall ſcatter your enemies from the Throne, and he ſhall magnifie you yet in the ſight of theſe Nations, and make the miſ-led people ſubmit themſelves willingly to your government. Sir, if you uſe well the Lords throne, on which you are ſet, then the two words in the place cited, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.23. ſpoken of <hi>Solomon</hi> ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the Throne of the Lord, <hi>He proſpered,</hi> and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> obeyed him, ſhall belong unto you, your people ſhall obey you in the Lord, and you ſhall proſper in the fight of the Nations round about.</p>
            <p>Then the Lord Chancellor went to the four corners of the Stage, the Lyon King of Armes going before him, and proclaimed his Majeſties free pardon, to all breakers of penal Statutes, and made offer thereof. Whereupon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cryed, <hi>God ſave the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then the King ſupported by the great Conſtable, Marſhal, and accompanied with the Chancellor, aroſe from the Throne, and went out at a door pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for that purpoſe, to a Stage, and ſheweth himſelf to the people with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, who clapped their hands, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a loud voice a long time, <hi>God ſave the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:96187:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:96187:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:96187:48"/>
            <p>Then the King returning, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down upon the Throne, delivered the Scepter to the Earl of <hi>Crawford</hi> and <hi>Lindſay,</hi> to be carried before him: Thereafter the Lyon King of Armes rehearſed the Royal Line of the Kings upwards, to <hi>Fergus</hi> the firſt.</p>
            <p>Then the Lyon called the Lords one by one, who kneeling, and holding their hands betwixt the Kings hands; did ſwear theſe words; <hi>By the Eternal and Almighty God, who liveth and reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for ever, I become your liege man, and Truth, and Faith ſhall bear unto you, and live and dy with you, againſt all manner of folks whatſoever, in your ſervice, according to the National Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And every one of them kiſſed the Kings left cheek.</p>
            <p>When theſe Solemnities were ended, the Miniſter ſtanding before the King on his Throne, pronounced this bleſſing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord bleſſe thee, and ſave thee, the Lord hear thee in the day of trouble; the Name of the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>defend thee: the Lord ſend thee help from the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, and ſtrengthen thee out of</hi> Sion, <hi>Amen:</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:96187:48"/>
            <p>After the bleſſing pronounced, the Miniſter went to the Pulpit, and had the following exhortation, the King ſitting ſtill upon the Throne. Ye have this day a King Crowned, and entred into Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, and his people, look, both King and people, that ye keep his Covenant, and beware of the breach of it: that you may be the more careful to keep it, I will lay a few things before you.</p>
            <p>I remember when the ſolemn League and Covenant was entred by both Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Commiſſioners from <hi>England</hi> being preſent in the Eaſt Kirk of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> a paſſage was cited out of <hi>Nehe.</hi> 6.13. Which I ſhall now again cite, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> required an Oath of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and people, to reſtore the morga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Lands, which they promiſed to do; after the Oath was tendred, in the 13. <hi>ver.</hi> he did ſhake his lap, and ſaid, <hi>So God ſhake out every man from his houſe, and from his labour, that performeth not his promiſe, even thus be he ſhaken out and emptied, and all the Congregati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns ſaid, Amen.</hi> Since the time many of thoſe who were in Covenant are ſhaken out of it, yea, they have ſhaken off the Covenant and laid it aſide. It is
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:96187:49"/> true they are proſpering this day, and think that they proſper by laying aſide the Covenant; but they will be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that word ſpoken then, ſhall not fall to the ground, God ſhall ſhake them out of their poſſeſſion, and empty them for their perfidious breach of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <p>The ſame I ſay to King and Nobles, and all that are in Covenant. If you break that Covenant, being ſo ſolemnly ſworn, all theſe who had touched your Crown, and ſworn to ſupport it, ſhall not be able to hold it on; but God will ſhake it off, and turn you from the Throne: and ye Noble men, who are aſſiſtant to the putting on of the Crown, and ſetting the King upon the Throne, if ye ſhall either aſſiſt, or adviſe the King to break the Covenant, and overturn the work of God, he ſhall ſhake you out of your poſſeſſions, and empty you of all your glory.</p>
            <p>Another paſſage I offer to your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, <hi>Jer.</hi> 34.8. after that <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> had promiſed to proclaim liberty to all the people, who were ſervants, and entred in a Covenant he and his Princes to let them go free, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Oath had let them go, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:96187:49"/> they cauſed the Servants to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, and brought them in ſubjection, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. What followeth upon this breach? <hi>ver.</hi> 15, 16. <hi>Ye were now turned and had done right in my ſight in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming liberty, but ye turned and made them ſervants again.</hi> And therefore, <hi>verſe</hi> 18, 19, 20, 21. <hi>I will give the men who have tranſgreſſed my Covenant, who have not performed the words of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which they made before me, when they cut the Calf in twain, and paſſed between the parts thereof, I will even give them into the hands of their enemies, into the hand of them that ſeek their life, even</hi> Zedekiah <hi>and his Princes.</hi> If the breach of a Covenant made for the liberty of Servants was ſo puniſhed, what ſhall be the puniſhment of the breach of a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant for Religion, and liberty of the people of God? There is nothing more terrible to Kings and Princes then to be given into the hands of enemies, that ſeek their life. If ye would eſcape this judgement, let King and Princes keep their Covenant made with God: Your enemies who ſeek your life, are in the land, if you break the Covenant, it may be feared, God will give you over unto them as a prey: but if ye yet keep Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:96187:50"/> it may be expected, God will keep you out of their hands.</p>
            <p>Let not the place ye heard opened be forgotten; for in it ye have an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Divine juſtice againſt <hi>Joaſh</hi> and the Princes for breaking that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.23. The Princes who inticed that breath, are deſtroyed: and in the 24. <hi>ver.</hi> it is ſaid: <hi>The Army of the Syrians came with a ſmall compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of men, and the Lord delivered a very great Hoſt into their hands: becauſe they had forſaken the Lord God of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: ſo they executed judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt</hi> Joaſh. And ver. 25. <hi>His own ſervants conſpired againſt him, and flew him on his bed, &amp;c.</hi> The conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Servants or Subjects againſt their King, is a wicked courſe: But God in his righteous judgements ſuffereth Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to conſpire and rebel againſt their Princes, becauſe they rebel againſt the Covenant made with God. I may ſay freely that a chief cauſe of the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the Kings houſe, hath been the Grandfathers breach of Covenant with God, and the fathers following ſteps, in oppoſing the work of God, and his Kirk within theſe Kingdoms; They broke Covenant with God, and men
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:96187:50"/> have broken Covenant with them: yea, moſt cruelly and perfidiouſly have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded the Royal Family, and trodden upon all Princely dignity.</p>
            <p>Be wiſe by their example; you are now ſitting upon the Throne of the Kingdome, and your Nobles about you there is one above you even <hi>Jeſus</hi> the King of <hi>Sion;</hi> and I, as his Servant dare not but be free with you; I charge you Sir in his Name, that you keep this Covenant in all points; if you break this Covenant, and come againſt this cauſe, I aſſure you the controverſie is not ended between God and your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, but will be carried on to further weakning, if not the overthrow of it; but if you ſhall keep this Covenant, and befriend the Kingdome of Chriſt, it may be from this day God ſhall begin to do you good, although your eſtate be very weak, God is able to raiſe you, and make you to Reign, maugre the oppoſition of all your Enemies; And howſoever it ſhall pleaſe the Lord to diſpoſe, you ſhall have a peace towards God, through Chriſt the Mediator.</p>
            <p>As for you who are Nobles and Peers of the Land, your ſhare is great in this day of Coronation ye have
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:96187:51"/> come and touched the Crown, and ſworn to ſupport it, ye have handled the Sword and Scepter, and have ſet down the King upon his Throne.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I Charge you keep your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, and ſee that ye never be moved your ſelves to come againſt it in any head or article thereof, and that ye give no counſel to the King to come againſt that Doctrine, Worſhip, Government and diſcipline of the kirk, eſtabliſhed in their Land as you would eſchew the Judgement of Covenant-breakers. If the King and ye who are engaged to ſupport the Crown, conſpire together againſt the kingdome of Chriſt, both ye that do ſupport and he that is ſupported, will fall together. I preſſe this the more, becauſe it is a rare thing to ſee a King and great men for Chriſt; in the long Catalogue of Kings which ye have heard recited this day, there will be found few to have been for Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I Charge you alſo, becauſe of your many Oaths to the King, that you keep them invoylably. Be Faithfull unto him according to your Covenant; the Oaths of God are upon you, if directly or indirectly, you do any thing againſt
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:96187:51"/> his ſtanding, God, by whom ye have ſworn will be avenged upon you for the breach of his Oath.</p>
            <p>And now I will cloſe up all in one word more to You, Sir, You are the onely Covenanted King with God and his people in the world: Many have obſtructed your entry in it: now ſeeing the Lord hath brought you in over all theſe Obſtructions, onely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to do what is contained therein; and it ſhall prove a happy time for You and Your Houſe. And becauſe you are entered in times of great difficulty, wherein ſmall ſtrength ſeems to remain with you in the eyes of the world for recovering your juſt power and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Therefore take counſell which <hi>David</hi> when he was dying gave to his Sonne <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.2, 3. <hi>Be ſtrong and ſhew thy ſelf a man, and keep the charge of the Lord thy God: to walk in his wayes, and keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, that thou mayſt proſper in all that thou doſt, and whitherſoever thou turneſt thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this <hi>Exhortation</hi> the Miniſter cloſed the whole action with prayer, and the xx. Pſalm being ſung, he diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the people with the Bleſſing.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:96187:52"/>
            <p>Then did the Kings Majeſty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from the Stage with the Crown upon his head, and receiving again the Scepter in his hand, returned with the whole Train in ſolemn manner to his Palace, the Sword being carried be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:96187:52"/>
            <head>A Declaration by the Kings Majeſty, to all His Subjects of the Kingdomes of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland. Printed at</hi> Edinburgh, <hi>1650.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. HIs Majeſty taking in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, that mercifull Diſpenſation of Divine Providence, by which he hath been recovered out of the ſnare of Evil Counſel; and having attained ſo full perſwaſion and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Loyalty of his People in <hi>Scotland,</hi> with whom he hath too long ſtood at a diſtance; and of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of their Cauſe, as to joyn in one Covenant with them, and to caſt himſelf and his Intereſts wholly upon God; and in all matters Civil, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Advice of his Parliament, and ſuch as ſhall be intruſted by them; and in all matters Eccleſiaſtick, the Advice of the General Aſſembly, and their Commiſſioners; and being ſenſible of his duty to God, and deſirous to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove himſelf to the conſciences of all his good Subjects, and to ſtop the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:96187:53"/> mouthes of his and their enemies and Traducers, doth in reference to his former Deportments, and as to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions for the future, Declare as followes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. Though his Majeſty, as a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Son be obliged to honour the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of his Royal Father, and have in eſtimation the perſon of his Mother; yet doth He deſire to be deeply hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and afflicted in Spirit before God, becauſe of His Fathers hearkning to, and following evil Counſels, and His oppoſition to the Work of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to the Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, by which ſo much of the bloud of the Lords People hath been ſhed in theſe Kingdomes; and for the Idolatry of his Mother, the Toleration whereof in the Kings Houſe, as it was matter of great ſtumbling to all the Proteſtant Churches; ſo could it not but be an high provocation againſt him who is a jealous God, viſiting the ſins of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers upon the Children: And albeit HIs Majeſty might extenuate His former Carriages and Actions, in following of the advice, and walking in the way of thoſe who are oppoſite to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and to the work of God, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:96187:53"/> might excuſe His delaying to give ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the juſt and neceſſary deſires of the Kirk and Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> from his education, and age, and evil Counſel, and Company, and from the ſtrange and inſolent proceedings of Sectaries againſt his Royal Father, and in reference to Religion, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Government of the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> to which He hath the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Right of Succeſſion; yet know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he hath to do with God, He doth ingeniouſly acknowledge all His own ſins, and all the ſins of his Fathers Houſe, craving pardon, and hoping for mercy and reconciliation through the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt. And as he doth value the conſtant Addreſſes that were made by his people to the Throne of grace on His behalf, when He ſtood in oppoſition to the work of God, as a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Teſtimony of Long-ſuffering, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and mercy upon the Lords part, and Loyalty upon theirs; ſo doth He hope, and ſhall take it as one of the greateſt tokens of their love and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Him and to His Government, That they will continue in Prayer and Supplication to God for Him; That the Lord who ſpared and preſerved
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:96187:54"/> Him to this day, notwithſtanding of all His own guiltineſſe, may be at peace with Him, and give him to fear the Lord His God, and to ſerve him with a perfect heart, and with a willing mind all the dayes of his life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. And his Majeſty having, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on full perſwaſion of the Juſtice and Equity of all the Heads and Articles thereof, now Sworn, and ſubſcribed the National Covenant of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Solemne League and Covenant of the three Kingdomes of <hi>Scotland, England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> doth declare, That He hath not ſworn and ſubſcribed theſe Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and entred into the Oath of God with his People, upon any ſiniſter In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and crooked Deſign, for attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing His own Ends; but, ſo far as Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Weakneſſe will permit, in the truth and ſincerity of His heart: And that He is firmly Reſolved in the Lords ſtrength, to adhere thereto, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute to the utmoſt of his power, all the Ends thereof, in his Station and Calling, really, conſtantly and ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all the dayes of his life. In order to which, He doth in the firſt place pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and Declare, That He will have
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:96187:54"/> no Enemies, but the Enemies of the Covenant; and that He will have no Friends, but the Friends of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: And therefore, as He doth now deteſt and abhorre all Popery, Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and Idolatry, together with Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, and all Errors, Hereſie, Schiſme and Prophaneneſſe, and reſolves not to tolerate, much leſſe allow any of theſe in any part of His Majeſties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, but to oppoſe Himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and to endeavour the Extirpacion thereof to the utm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt of his power; ſo doth He as a Chriſtian Exhort, and as a King require, That all ſuch of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who have ſtood in Oppoſition to the Solemn League and Covenant, and Work of Reformation, upon a pretence of Kingly Intereſt, or any other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text whatſoever, to lay down their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt the Cauſe and People of God, and to ceaſe to prefer the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Man to the Intereſt of God; which hath been one of thoſe things which hath occaſioned many Troubles and Calamities in theſe Kingdomes, and being inſiſted into, will be ſo far from Eſtabliſhing of the Kings Throne, that it will prove an Idol of Jealouſie, to provoke unto wrath him who is King
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:96187:55"/> King of kings, and Lord of lords. The King ſhall alwayes eſteem them beſt Servants, and moſt loyal Subjects, who ſerve Him, and ſeek His Greatneſſe in a right line of ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination unto God; <hi>Giving unto God the things that are Gods, and unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars:</hi> And Reſolveth, not to love or countenance any who have ſo little Conſcience and Piety, as to follow his Intereſts with a prejudice to the Goſpel and Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt, which He looks not upon as a duty, but as flattery, and driving Self-Deſignes, under a pretence of maintaining Royall Authority and Greatneſſe. <hi>Secondly,</hi> His Majeſty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing convinced in Conſcience of the exceeding great Sinfulneſs and Unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of that Treaty and Peace made with the Bloody <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, who trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly ſhed the Blood of ſo many of His Faithful and Loyal Subjects in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of allowing unto them the Liberty of the Popiſh Religion; for the which He doth from His heart deſire to be deeply humbled before the Lord: And likewiſe conſidering how many Breaches have been on their part, Doth Declare the ſame to be void, and that
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:96187:55"/> His Majeſty is abſolved therefrom; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truly ſorry that He ſhould have ſought unto ſo unlawful Help for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of him to His Throne, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving, for the time to come, rather to chooſe Affliction than Sin. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As His Majeſty did in the late Treaty with His people in this Kingdom, agree to recall and annull all Commiſſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any of His Subjects who did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the Covenant and Monarchical Government in any of His Kingdoms: So doth He now Declare, That by Commiſſionating of ſome perſons by Sea againſt the people of <hi>England,</hi> He did not intend Damage or Injury to His oppreſt and harmleſſe Subjects in tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Kingdom, who follow their Trade of Merchandize in their lawful Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, but onely the oppoſing and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of thoſe who had Uſurped the Government; and not only bar Him from his juſt Right, but alſo exerciſe an Arbitrary Power over his people, in thoſe things which concern their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Conſciences and Eſtates: And as ſince His coming into <hi>Scotland</hi> He hath given no Commiſſions againſt any of His Subjects in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſo He doth hereby Aſſure and Declare,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:96187:56"/> That He will give none to their preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice or damage; and whatever ſhall be the Wrongs of theſe Uſurpers, That He will be far from avenging theſe upon any who are free thereof, by interru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting or ſtopping the liberty of Trade and Merchandize, or otherwiſe, That He will ſeek their good, and to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt employ His Royal Power, That they may be protected and defended againſt the unjuſt Violence of all men whatſoever. And albeit His Majeſty deſires to conſtruct well of the Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe (in reference to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty) who have been active in Council or Arms againſt the Covenant; yet, being convinced that it doth conduce for the Honour of God, the Good of his Cauſe, and His Own Honour and Happineſſe, and for the Peace and Safety of theſe Kingdoms, That ſuch be not employed in Places of Power and Truſt, He doth Declare, That He will not employ, nor give Commiſſions to any ſuch, until they have not onely taken, or renewed the Covenant, but alſo have given ſufficient evidences of their Integrity, Carriage and Affection to the Work of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſhall be declared capable of Truſt by the Parliament of either King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:96187:56"/> reſpective: And His Majeſty, upon the ſame grounds, doth hereby recal all Commiſſions given to any ſuch perſons; conceiving all ſuch perſons will ſo much tender a good Underſtanding betwixt Him and His Subjects, and the ſettling and preſerving a firm Peace in theſe kingdoms, That they will not grudge nor repine at His Majeſties Reſolutions and proceedings herein, much leſs upon diſcontent act any any thing in a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded way, unto the raiſing of New Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, eſpecially ſince upon their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious and good deportment, there is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe left unto them in manner above expreſs'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. And as His Majeſty hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſatisfaction to the juſt and neceſſary Deſires of the kirk and kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſo doth He hereby aſſure and declare, That He is no leſs willing and deſirous to give ſatisfaction to the juſt and neceſſary Deſires of his good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> and in token thereof, if the Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> ſitting in Freedome ſhall think fit to preſent unto Him the propoſitions of Peace, agreed upon by both kingdoms, He will not only accord to the ſame, and ſuch alterations there:
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:96187:57"/> anent, as the Houſes of Parliament, in regard of the Conſtitution of affairs, and the good of his Majeſty and His Kingdoms ſhall judge neceſſary, but do what is further neceſſary for proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ends of the Solemne League and Covenant, eſpecially in thoſe things which concern the Reformation of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in Doctrine, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Diſcipline and Government; That not only the Directory of Worſhip, the Confeſſion of Faith and Catechiſm, but alſo the Propoſitions and Directory for Church-Government, accorded upon by the Synod of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> may be ſettled; and that the Church of <hi>England</hi> may enjoy the full Liberty and Freedome of all Aſſembles, and power of Kirk-Cenſures, and of all the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, according to the Rule of his own Word: And that whatſoever is commanded by the God of Heaven, may be diligently done for the Houſe of the God of Heaven; and, whatever heretofore hath been the ſuggeſtions of ſome to him to render his Majeſty jealous of His Parliament, and of the Servants of God: Yet as He hath declared, that in <hi>Scotland</hi> He will hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to their Counſel, and follow their
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:96187:57"/> Advice in thoſe things that concern that Kingdome and Kirk; So doth he alſo declare His firm Reſolution to manage the Government of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England</hi> by the Advice of His Parliament, conſiſting of an Houſe of Lords, and of an Houſe of Commons there; and in thoſe things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern Religion, to prefer the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, to all other counſels whatſoever. And that all the world may ſee how much he ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the ſafety of his people, and how precious their bloud is in his ſight, and how deſirous he is to recover his Crown and Government in <hi>England</hi> by peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able meanes; as he doth eſteem the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of thoſe who firſt engaged in the Covenant, and have ſince that time faithfully followed the ends thereof, to be Duty to God, and Loyalty to Him; ſo is he willing in regard of others, who have been involved in theſe late com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions in <hi>England,</hi> againſt Religion and Government, to paſſe an Act of Oblivion, excepting only ſome few in that Nation, who have been chief Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructers of the work of Reformation, and chief Authors of the change of the Government, and of the Murther of his
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:96187:58"/> Royal Father. Provided, That theſe who are to have the benefit of this Act, lay down Armes, and return unto the obedience of their lawful Soveraign.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. The Committee of Eſtates of the Kingdome, and General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared ſo fully in what concernes the Sectaries, and the preſent Deſignes, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and Actings of their Army, againſt the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland:</hi> And the ſame Committee &amp; Aſſembly having ſufficiently laid open publick Dangers &amp; Duties, both upon the right hand &amp; the left; It is not needful for His Majeſty to adde any thing thereunto; except, That in thoſe things He doth commend and approve th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, and that He Reſolves to live and dye with them, and his loyal Subjects, in proſecution of the Ends of the Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. And whereas that prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing party in <hi>England,</hi> after all their ſtrange Uſurpations, and inſolent Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in that Land; Do not only keep His Majeſty from the Government of that Kingdome by force of Armes, but alſo have now invaded the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who have deſerved better things at their hands, and againſt whom
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:96187:58"/> they have no juſt quarrel; His Majeſty doth therefore deſire and expect, That all his good Subjects in <hi>England,</hi> who are, and reſolve to be faithful to God and to their King, according to the Covenant, will lay hold upon ſuch an opportunity, and uſe their utmoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to promote the Covenant, and all the ends thereof; and to recover and re-eſtabliſh the Ancient Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> (under which for many Generations, it did flouriſh in peace and plenty at home, and in Reputation abroad) and Priviledges of the Parliament, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Juſt Liberty of the People. His Majeſty deſires to aſſure himſelf, That there doth remain in theſe ſo much confidence of their duty to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, their King and Countrey, and ſo many ſparkles of the ancient <hi>Engliſh</hi> Valour, which ſhined ſo eminently in their Noble Anceſtors, as will put them on to beſtir themſelves for the breaking the Yoak of thoſe mens Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions from off their Necks. Shall men of Conſcience and Honour ſet Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Liberties and Government at ſo low a rate, as not rather to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go any hazard, before they be thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:96187:59"/> of them? Will not all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous men count any Death more tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables than to live in ſervitude all their dayes? And will not Poſterity blame thoſe who dare attempt nothing for themſelves, and for their Children, in ſo good a Cauſe, in ſuch an Exigent? Whereas if they gather themſelves, and take courage, putting on a Reſolution anſwerable to ſo Noble and juſt an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize, they ſhall honour God, and gain themſelves the Reputation of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, worthy Patriots, and loyal Subjects, and be called <hi>The Repairers of the Breach,</hi> by the preſent, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Generations; and they may certainly promiſe to themſelves a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from God upon ſo juſt and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable undertaking for the Lord, and for his Cauſe, for their own Liberties, their Native King and countrey, and the unvaluable good and happineſſe of their Poſterity. Whatever hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been his Majeſties guiltineſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and the bad ſucceſſe that theſe have had who owned his Affairs, whilſt he ſtood in oppoſition to the Work of God; yet the ſtate of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion being now altered, and His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty having obtained Mercy to be on
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:96187:59"/> Gods ſide, and to prefer Gods Intereſt before his Own, He hopes, That the Lord will be gracious and countenance his own Cauſe, in the hands of weak and ſinful Inſtruments, againſt all Enemies whatſoever. This is all that can be ſaid by His Majeſty at preſent, to thoſe in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> at ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and as they ſhall acquit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at this time in the active diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their neceſſary Duties, ſo ſhall they be accepted before God, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared to his Majeſty, and their Names had in remembrance throughout the World. Given at Our Court of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmlin,</hi> the ſixteenth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1650. and in the ſecond year of Our Raign.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:96187:60"/>
            <head>The great danger of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-refuſing, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-breaking.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 Tim. 3.3.</bibl>
               <q>—<hi>Truce-breakers;</hi> or, Covenant-breakers.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the beginning of the Chapter, the Apoſtle tells us the condition that the Church of God ſhould be in, in the laſt dayes. <hi>This know alſo, that in the laſt dayes perilous times ſhall come.</hi> In the ſecond Verſe he tells us the reaſon why <hi>theſe</hi> times ſhould be <hi>ſuch hard and dangerous times; For men ſhall be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of themſelves, covetous, &amp;c.</hi> The reaſon is not drawn from the <hi>miſeries</hi> and <hi>calamities</hi> of the laſt times, but from the ſins and iniquities of the laſt times. <hi>It is ſin and iniquity that makes times truly perilous.</hi> Sin and ſin only, takes away Gods love and favour from a Nation, and makes God turn an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to it. <hi>Sin cauſeth God</hi> to take away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e purity and power of his <hi>Ordinances</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:96187:60"/> from a Nation. <hi>Sin</hi> makes all the creatures to be armed againſt us, and makes our own <hi>conſcience</hi> to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us. <hi>Sin</hi> is the <hi>cauſe</hi> of all the <hi>cauſes</hi> of perilous times. <hi>Sin</hi> is the cauſe of our <hi>civil warres,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Sin</hi> is the cauſe of our <hi>diviſions, Jam.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Sin</hi> is the cauſe why men fall into ſuch dangerous errours, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Sin</hi> brings ſuch kinds of judgements which no other enemy can bring. <hi>Sin</hi> brings inviſible, ſpiritual, and eternal judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. It is <hi>ſin</hi> that makes <hi>God</hi> give over a Nation to a <hi>ſenſe, Rom.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Sin</hi> makes all times dangerous. Let the times be never ſo proſperous, yet if they be ſinful times, they are times truly dangerous. And if they be not <hi>ſinful,</hi> they are not dangerous, though never ſo miſerable. It is <hi>ſin</hi> that makes <hi>Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> to be the fruits of <hi>Gods revenging</hi> wrath, part of the <hi>curſe</hi> due to ſin, and a beginning of <hi>Hell.</hi> It is <hi>ſin,</hi> and <hi>ſin</hi> only, that imbitters every affliction. Let us for ever look upon ſin through theſe <hi>Scripture ſpectacles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in four verſes reckons up 19 <hi>ſins,</hi> as the cauſes of the miſeries of the laſt dayes. I may truly call theſe 19 <hi>ſins, Englands Looking-glaſſe,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:96187:61"/> we may ſee what are the <hi>clouds</hi> that <hi>eclipſe</hi> Gods <hi>countenance</hi> from ſhining upon us: the Mountains that lye in the way to hinder the ſettlement of <hi>Church-diſcipline.</hi> Even theſe 19 <hi>ſim</hi> which are as an <hi>Iron whip</hi> of 19 <hi>ſtrings,</hi> with which God is whipping <hi>England</hi> at this day; which are as 19 <hi>Faggots</hi> with which God is burning and devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>England.</hi> My purpoſe is not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeak of all theſe ſins: Onely let me propound a <hi>Divine project</hi> how to make the times happy for ſoul and body. And that is, To ſtrike at the root of all miſery, which is <hi>ſin and iniquity.</hi> To repent for, and from all theſe 19 ſins, which are as the <hi>Oyl</hi> that feedeth, and encreaſeth the flame that is now conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of us. For becauſe men are <hi>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of themſelves, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque ad contemptum Dei &amp; Reipublicae.</hi> Becauſe men drive their own deſignes not only to the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, but contempt of God and the Common-wealth. Becauſe men are <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous,</hi> lovers of the world more then lovers of God. Becauſe they are <hi>proud</hi> in <hi>head, heart, looks</hi> and <hi>apparel.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are <hi>unthankful,</hi> turning the mercies of God into inſtruments of ſin, and making Darts with Gods bleſſing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:96187:61"/> to ſhoot againſt God. Becauſe men are <hi>unholy</hi> and <hi>beady,</hi> and make many covenants, and keep none. Becauſe they are (as the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth) <hi>Devils,</hi> acting the Devils part in accuſing the brethren, and in bearing falſe witneſſe one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Becauſe they have a <hi>form of godlineſſe, denying the power</hi> thereof, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hence it is that theſe times are ſo ſad and bloudy. Theſe are thine enemies, O <hi>England,</hi> that have brought thee into this deſolate condition! if ever God lead us back into the wilderneſſe, it will be becauſe of theſe ſinnes. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if ever you would have bleſſed dayes, you muſt make it your great bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe to remove theſe 19 mountaines, and repent of theſe land-devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and ſoul-deſtroying abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>At this time I ſhall pick out the firſt, and the tenth ſin to ſpeak on. The firſt is <hi>ſelf-love,</hi> which is placed in the <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front</hi> as the cauſe of all the reſt. <hi>Self-love</hi> is not only a ſin that makes the <hi>times perilous,</hi> but it is the cauſe of all thoſe ſins that makes the times perilous. For becauſe men are <hi>lovers of themſelves,</hi> therefore they are <hi>covetous, proud, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:96187:62"/> &amp;c.</hi> The tenth ſinne is <hi>truce-breaking,</hi> and for fear leſt the time ſhould prevent me, I will begin with this ſinne firſt.</p>
            <p>The tenth ſin then is <hi>truce-breakers;</hi> or, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.33. <hi>Covenant-breakers.</hi> The Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth three things. Firſt ſuch as are <hi>foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deris neſcii,</hi> as <hi>Beza</hi> renders it; or as others, <hi>infoederabiles;</hi> that is, ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to enter into Covenant. Or ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuch as are <hi>foedifragi, qui pacta non ſervant,</hi> (as <hi>Eſtius</hi> hath it) or <hi>ſine fide,</hi> as <hi>Ambroſe;</hi> that is, ſuch as break faith and Covenant. Or thirdly, ſuch as are <hi>implacabiles;</hi> or as others, <hi>ſine pace;</hi> that is, ſuch as are <hi>implacable,</hi> and <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to this threefold ſenſe of the word, I ſhall gather theſe three ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Doct. 1. <hi>That to be a Covenant-refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, is a ſin that makes the times pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Doct. 2. <hi>That to be a Covenant break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, is a ſin that makes the times pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Doct. 3. <hi>That to be a peace hater, or a truce-hater, is a ſin that makes the times perilous.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:96187:62"/>
            <p>To begin with the firſt.</p>
            <p>Doctrine the firſt. <hi>That to be a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-refuſer, is a ſinne that makes the times perilous.</hi> To be <hi>foederis neſcius,</hi> or <hi>indefoederabilis.</hi> For the underſtanding of this, you muſt know that there are two <hi>ſorts of Covenants.</hi> There are <hi>divel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> and <hi>helliſh Covenants,</hi> and there are <hi>godly and religious Covenants.</hi> Firſt, there are divelliſh Covenants, ſuch as <hi>Acts</hi> 23.12. and <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 28.15. ſuch as the <hi>holy league</hi> (as it was unjuſtly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) <hi>in France</hi> againſt the <hi>Hugonites,</hi> and that of our Gunpowder Traytors in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to refuſe to take ſuch Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, is not to make the times perilous, but the taking of them makes the times perilous. Secondly, there are <hi>godly Covenants;</hi> ſuch as <hi>Job</hi> 31.1. I have made a <hi>Covenant with mine eyes, why then ſhould I think upon a maid?</hi> Such as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>I have ſworn I will perform it, that I will keep thy righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> ſuch as 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.14. And ſuch as this is, which you are met to take this day. For you are to ſwear to ſuch things which you are bound to endeavour after, though you did not ſwear. Your ſwearing is not <hi>ſolum vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum,</hi>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:96187:63"/> but <hi>novum vinculum,</hi> is not <hi>the onely,</hi> but onely a <hi>new</hi> and another bond to tye you to the obedience of the things you ſwear unto; which are ſo excellent and ſo glorious, that if God give thoſe that take it a heart to keep it, it will make theſe three Kingdomes the glory of the world. And as one of the <hi>Reverend Commiſſioners of Scotland</hi> ſaid when it was firſt taken in a moſt ſolemn manner at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> by the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and the Aſſembly; <hi>That if the Pope ſhould have this Covenant written upon a wall over againſt him ſitting in his chair, it would be unto him like the hand-writing to</hi> Belſhazzar; <hi>cauſing the joynts to looſe, and his knees to ſmioe one againſt another.</hi> And I may adde, that if it be faithfully and fully kept, it will make all the <hi>Divels in Hell</hi> to tremble, as fearing leſt their Kingdome ſhould not long ſtand. Now then for a man to be an <hi>Anticovenanter,</hi> and to be ſuch a <hi>Covenant-refuſer,</hi> it muſt needs be a ſin that makes the times perilous.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1. Becauſe you ſhall find in Scripture that when any Nation did enter into a ſolem religious Covenant, God did exceedingly bleſs and proſper
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:96187:63"/> that Nation after that time; As appears 2 Chron. 15.19. 2 Kings 11.20. And we have a promiſe for it, Deut. 21.12, 13. <hi>That thou ſhouldeſt enter into covenant with the Lord thy God, &amp;c. That he may eſtabliſh thee to day for a people unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and that he may be unto thee a God, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore to be a <hi>Covenant-refuſer,</hi> is to make our miſeries perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ual.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 2. Becauſe as it is the higheſt act of <hi>Gods love</hi> to man, to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to engage himſelf by <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> to be his God, ſo it is the higheſt demonſtration of mans <hi>love to God,</hi> to bind himſelf by <hi>Oath and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> to be Gods. There is nothing obligeth <hi>God</hi> more to us, then to ſee us willing to tye and bind our ſelves faſt unto his ſervice. And therefore they that in this ſenſe are <hi>Anti-covenanters,</hi> are ſons of <hi>Belial;</hi> that refuſe the yoak of the Lord, that ſay, as <hi>Pſalm</hi> 2.3. <hi>Let us break his bands aſunder, and caſt away his cords from us;</hi> ſuch as <hi>Oderunt vincula pietatis,</hi> which is a ſoul-deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and land-deſtroying ſin:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 3. Becauſe that the union of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> into one <hi>Covenant,</hi> is the chief, if not the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:96187:64"/> onely <hi>preſervative</hi> of them at this time You find in our <hi>Engliſh Chroniclers,</hi> that <hi>England</hi> was never deſtroyed, but when divided within it ſelf. Our civil divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions brought in the <hi>Romans,</hi> the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Danes,</hi> and <hi>Normans.</hi> But now the <hi>Anti-covenanters,</hi> he divides the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment within it ſelf, and the City within it ſelf, and <hi>England</hi> againſt it ſelf; he is as a <hi>ſtone ſeparated</hi> from the building, which is of no uſe to it ſelf, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ruine of the building. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is called in <hi>Scripture</hi> the <hi>corner-ſtone,</hi> which is a <hi>ſtone</hi> that unites two ends of a building together; <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is a ſtone of union, and therefore they that ſow diviſion, and ſtudy unjuſt ſeparation, have little of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in them. When the <hi>ten tribes</hi> began to divide from the other two tribes, they preſently began to war one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to ruine one another. The <hi>Anti-covenanter</hi> he divides, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, and diſunites; and therefore he makes the times perilous.</p>
            <p>My chief aim is at the ſecond Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; which is,</p>
            <p>Doct. 2. <hi>That for a Covenant-taker to be a Covenant-breaker, is a ſin that makes the times perilous.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:96187:64"/>
            <p>For the opening of this point, I muſt diſtinguiſh again of <hi>Covenants.</hi> There are <hi>civil,</hi> and there are religious <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants.</hi> A <hi>civil Covenant,</hi> is a <hi>Covenant</hi> between <hi>man</hi> and <hi>man;</hi> and of this the Text is <hi>primarily,</hi> though not onely to be underſtood. Now for a man to break promiſe and Covenant with his brother, is a <hi>land-ſtroying,</hi> and <hi>ſoul-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring abomination.</hi> We read 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. that becauſe <hi>Saul</hi> had broken the <hi>Covenant</hi> that <hi>Joſhua</hi> made with the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites,</hi> God ſent a famine in <hi>David</hi>'s time of three years continuance: To teach us, <hi>that if we falſifie our Word and Oath,</hi> God will avenge <hi>covenant-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, though it be forty years after.</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous is that text, <hi>Jer.</hi> 34.17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Becauſe the Princes and the People brake the covenant which they had made with their ſervants</hi> (though but their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants) God tells them. <hi>Becauſe ye have not hearkned unto me in proclaiming li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty every one to his brother, &amp;c. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I proclaim liberty for you, ſaith the Lord to the ſword, to the peſtilence, and and to the famine: and I will make you to be removed into all the Kingdomes of the Earth; &amp;c.</hi> We read alſo <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17.18, 19, 20. That God tells <hi>Zedekiah</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:96187:65"/> he brake the covenant he had made with the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that therefore <hi>he would recompence upon his head the oath that he had deſpiſed, and the covenant that he had broken, and would bring him to Babylon, and plead with him there for the treſpaſſe which he had treſpaſſed againſt the Lord. David</hi> tells us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.4. that it is a ſin that ſhuts a man out of heaven. The <hi>Turkiſh</hi> hiſtories tell us of a covenant of peace made between <hi>Amurath</hi> the great <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and how the <hi>Pope</hi> abſolved <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> from his oath, and provoked him to renew the war. In which war the <hi>Turk</hi> being put to the worſt, and deſpairing of victory, pulls out a paper which he had in his boſome wherein the league was written; and ſaid, <hi>O thou God of the Chriſtians, if thou beeſt a true God, be revenged of thoſe that without cauſe have broken the league made by calling upon thy name.</hi> And the ſtory ſaith, that after he had ſpoken theſe words, he had as it were a <hi>new heart</hi> and <hi>ſpirit put into him, and his ſouldiers,</hi> and that they obtained a glorious victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Ladiſlaus.</hi> Thus God avenged the quarrel of mans covenant. The like ſtory we have of <hi>Rodolphus Duke of Swevia,</hi>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:96187:65"/> who by the <hi>Popes</hi> inſtigation waged war with <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth <hi>Emperour of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> to whom he had ſworn the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The Pope ſent a <hi>Crown</hi> to him with this Motto, <hi>Petra dedit Petro, Petrus dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dema Rodolpho;</hi> but in the fight it chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that <hi>Rodolphus</hi> loſt his <hi>right hand;</hi> and falling ſick upon it he called for it, and ſaid, <hi>Spectate hanc dextram legitima <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>upplicia expendentem, quae fidem ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento munitam, &amp; Henrico Domino meo datam, vobis urgentibus, praeter aequum &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us temere violavit.</hi> Behold this right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and with which I ſubſcribed to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, with which I have violated my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath, and therefore I am rightly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. I will not trouble you in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the gallant ſtory of <hi>Regulus,</hi> that thoſe rather to expoſe himſelf to a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el death, then to falſifie his oath to the <hi>Carthaginians.</hi> The ſum of all is, if it be ſuch a <hi>crying abomination</hi> to break <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant</hi> between man and man; and if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch perſons are accounted as the <hi>off-ſcouring</hi> of men, not worthy to live in a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> no not in a <hi>heathen Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weal;</hi> If it be a ſin that draws down ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eance from heaven, and excludes a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom heaven; much more for a man to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nter into a covenant with the great Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:96187:66"/> and to break ſuch a religious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement; this muſt needs be a deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſoul-damning ſin. And of ſuch religious covenants I am now to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>There are two covenants that God made with man, <hi>a covenant of nature,</hi> &amp; <hi>a covenant of grace.</hi> The covenant of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (or of works) was made with <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am,</hi> and all mankind in him. This covenant <hi>Adam</hi> broke, and <hi>God</hi> preſently had a quarrel againſt him for breaking of it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.8, 9. And to avenge the quarre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>covenant,</hi> he was thruſt out of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe;</hi> and there was a <hi>ſword</hi> alſo placed at the Eaſt end of the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> to avenge covenant-breaking. And by na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture we are all children of wrath, heir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of hell, becauſe of the breach of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> covenant. And therefore we ſhould never think of <hi>original ſin,</hi> or of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſinfulneſſe and curſedneſſe of our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral condition, but we ſhould remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what a grievous ſinne Covenant-breaking is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after man was fallen, God wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleaſed to ſtrike a new covenant, wich i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> uſually called a covenant of grace, or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reconciliation; a copy of which you ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> read, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.7 8, 9. This was firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pounded to <hi>Adam</hi> by way of <hi>promiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:96187:66"/> Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>The Seed of the woman ſhall bruiſe the Serpents head.</hi> And then to <hi>Abram</hi> by way of <hi>Covenant,</hi> Gen. 17. <hi>In thy ſeed ſhall all the nations of the world be bleſſed.</hi> And then to <hi>Moſes</hi> by way of Teſtament, <hi>Ex.</hi> 33. It is nothing elſe but <hi>the free and gracious tender of Jeſus Chriſt, and all his rich purchaſes to all the loſt and undone ſons of</hi> Adam, <hi>that ſhall believe in him; or</hi> as the phraſe is <hi>Iſai.</hi> 56.4. <hi>that ſhall take bold of the covenant.</hi> Now you muſt know that Baptiſme is a ſeal of this covenant, and that all that are baptized, do ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally at leaſt, engage themſelves to walk before God, and to be upright; and God likewiſe engageth himſelf to be their God. This covenant is likewiſe renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when we come to the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> wherein we bind our ſelves by a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental oath unto thankfulneſſe to God for Chriſt. Adde further, that beſides this general covenant of grace whereof the Sacraments are ſeales, there are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and perſonal, and family, &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional covenants. Thus <hi>Job</hi> had his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Job.</hi> 20. and <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119.106. And when he came to be King, he joyned in a covenant with his people to ſerve the Lord. Thus <hi>Aſa, Jehoiada,</hi> and <hi>Joſiah,</hi> &amp;c. Thus the people of Iſrael
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:96187:67"/> had not onely a covenant in <hi>circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> but renewed a covenant in <hi>Horeb,</hi> and in <hi>Moab;</hi> and did often again and again bind themſelves to God by vow and covenant. And thus the Churches of the Chriſtians, beſides the vow in Baptiſme, have many perſonal and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional engagements unto God by cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which are nothing elſe but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations, and particular applications of that firſt vow in Baptiſme. Of this nature is that you are to renew this day, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now give me leave to ſhew you what a <hi>ſword-procuring</hi> and <hi>ſoul-undoing</hi> ſin, this ſin of <hi>Covenant-breaking</hi> is; and then the reaſon of it. Famous is that text, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.25. <hi>And I will ſend my ſword which ſhall avenge the quarrel of my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi> The words in Hebrew run thus; I will avenge the avengement. In Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Latins <hi>ulciſcar, ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem;</hi> which importeth thus much. That God is at open war and at <hi>publick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance</hi> with thoſe that break his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, he is not only angry with them, but he will be revenged of them. The Lord hath a controverſie with all cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-breakers, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4 1. or as it is <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.23. The Lord will walk contrary to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:96187:67"/> them. In the 29 of <hi>Deuter.</hi> firſt God takes his people into covenant, and then he tells them of the happy condition they ſhould be in if they did keep the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. But if they did break covenant, he tells them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25. <hi>That the Lord will not ſpare him; but the anger of the Lord and his jealouſies ſhall ſmoak againſt that man, and all the curſes that are written in this book ſhall lie upon him, and the Lord ſhall blot out his name from under heaven. And the Lord ſhall ſeparate him, &amp;c. And when the nations ſhall ſay, Wherefore hath the Lord done thus unto this land? What meaneth rhe heat of this anger? Then ſhall men ſay, Becauſe they have forſaken the covenant of the Lord God of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp;c.</hi> This was the ſin that cauſed God to ſend his people of Iſrael into captivity, and to remove the candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick from the <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches. It is for this ſin that the ſword is now devouring <hi>Germany Ireland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. God hath ſent his ſword to avenge the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of his covenant.</p>
            <p>The reaſons why this ſin is a God-provoking ſin, are,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe that <hi>to ſin againſt the covenant,</hi> is a greater ſin than to <hi>ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:96187:68"/> a Commandement</hi> of God, or to ſin againſt a <hi>promiſe,</hi> or to ſin againſt an <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance</hi> of God. Firſt, it is a greater ſin than to break a <hi>Commandement</hi> of God. For the more mercy there is in the thing we ſin againſt, the greater is the ſin. Now there is more mercy in a <hi>covenant,</hi> then in a bare <hi>Commandement.</hi> The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement tells us our duty, but gives no power to do it. But the covenant of grace gives power to do what it requires to be done. And therefore if it be a hell-procuring ſin to break the leaſt of Gods Commandements, much more to be a Covenant-breaker, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28, 29. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is a greater ſin then to ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a <hi>promiſe</hi> of God; becauſe a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is a promiſe joyn'd with an oath, it is a mutuall ſtipulation between God and us. And therefore if it be a great ſin to break promiſe, much more to break covenant. Thirdly, it is a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſin than to ſin againſt an <hi>Ordinance,</hi> becauſe the <hi>covenant</hi> is the root and ground of all the <hi>Ordinances</hi> It is by vertue of the <hi>covenant</hi> that we are made partakers of <hi>the Ordinances.</hi> The <hi>word</hi> is the book of the <hi>covenant,</hi> and the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> are the ſeales of the <hi>covenant.</hi> And if it be a ſin of an high nature to ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:96187:68"/> the book of the <hi>covenant,</hi> and the <hi>ſeals</hi> of the <hi>covenant</hi> much more againſt the <hi>covenant,</hi> it ſelf. To break covenant is a <hi>fundamental ſin,</hi> it raſeth the very <hi>foundation of Chriſtianity,</hi> becauſe the Covenant is the foundation of all the priviledges and prerogatives, &amp; hopes of the <hi>Saints</hi> of God. And therefore we read, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. that a <hi>ſtranger from the covenant</hi> is one without <hi>hope.</hi> All hope of heaven is cut off where the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is willingly broken. <hi>To break co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is an univerſal ſin,</hi> it includes all other ſins. By vertue of the Covenant we tye our ſelves to the obedience of Gods Commandements, we give up our ſelves to the guidance of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> we take him for our <hi>Lord and King.</hi> All the promiſes of this life and that that is to come, are contained within the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. The <hi>Ordinances</hi> are fruits of the Covenant. And therefore they that forſake the Covenant, commit <hi>many ſins in one,</hi> and bring not only many, but all curſes upon their heads. The ſum of the firſt Argument is, <hi>If the Lord will avenge the quarrel of his commandement,</hi> if God was avenged upon the <hi>ſtick-ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer</hi> for <hi>breaking</hi> the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> much more will he be <hi>avenged</hi> upon a <hi>covenant
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:96187:69"/> breaker.</hi> If God will avenge the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of a <hi>promiſe,</hi> if the <hi>quarrel</hi> of an <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance:</hi> if they that reject the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances ſhall be puniſhed; <hi>Of how much ſeverer puniſhment ſhall they be thought worthy, that trample under their feet the blood of the Covenant?</hi> If God was avenged of thoſe that abuſed the <hi>Ark</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> much more will he puniſh thoſe that abuſe the <hi>Angell</hi> of the <hi>Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Reaſon why <hi>covenant-breaking</hi> is ſuch a Land-ſtro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing ſin is, becauſe it is a ſolemn and ſerious thing to enter into <hi>covenant with God;</hi> a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſuch great weight &amp; importance, that it is impoſſible but God ſhould be exceedingly provoked with thoſe that ſlight it and diſ-reſpect it. The Vow in <hi>Baptiſme</hi> is the <hi>firſt,</hi> the moſt generall and the ſolemneſt vow that ever any Chriſtian took, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he doth not only promiſe, but engage himſelf by covenant in the ſight of God and his holy Angels to be the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Jeſus Chriſt, and therefore God will not hold him guiltleſs that breaks this Vow. The ſolemnity and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe of covenant-taking conſiſteth in three things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:96187:69"/>1. Becauſe it is made with the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Majeſty</hi> of Heaven and Earth, who will not be trifled and baffled withall. And therefore what <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> ſaid to his Judges, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.6. <hi>Take heed what you doe, for ye judge not for men, but for the Lord, who is with you in judgements; wherefore now let the fear of the Lord be upon you, &amp;c.</hi> The like I may ſay to every one that enters into covenant this day. <hi>Take heed what you do, for it is the Lords covenant, and there is no iniquity with the Lord, wherfore now let the fear of the Lord be upon you. For our God is a holy God, he is a jealous God, he will not forgive your tranſgreſſions, nor your ſins,</hi> as <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſaith, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the articles of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant are weighty and of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. In the Covenant of grace God ingageth himſelf to give Chriſt, and with him, all temporal, ſpiritual, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal bleſſings, and we engage our ſelves to be his faithful ſervants all our dayes. In this <hi>Covenant</hi> we oblige our ſelves to doe great matters that neerly concern the glory of God, the good of our own ſoules, and the happineſſe of three Kingdomes. And in ſuch holy and heavenly things which ſo
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:96187:70"/> neerly concern our everlaſting eſtate, to dally and trifle muſt needs incenſe the anger of the great Jehovah.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The manner uſed both by <hi>Jewes, Heathen,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> in entring into <hi>Covenant,</hi> doth clearly ſet out the <hi>weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe</hi> of it, and what a horrible ſin it is to break it. The cuſtome amongſt the <hi>Jewes</hi> will appear by divers texts of Scripture: <hi>Jer.</hi> 34.18. it is ſaid, <hi>And I will give the men that have tranſgreſſed my covenant which they had made before me, when they cut the Calf in twain, and paſſed between the parts thereof.</hi> The words they uſed when they paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the parts where, So God divide me, if I keep not covenant. <hi>Neh.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> took an oath of the Prieſts, and ſhook his lap and ſaid, <hi>So God ſhake out every man from his houſe, and from his labour, that performeth not this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, even thus be he ſhaken out and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptied. And all the Congregation ſaid, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> In the 15. of <hi>Geneſis Abraham</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the Heifer, and ſhe-Goat, and a Ram, &amp;c. <hi>And when the Sun was down a ſmoaking furnace and burning lamp paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed between theſe pieces.</hi> This did repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Gods preſence, ſaith <hi>Clemens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus,</hi> and it was as if God ſhould ſay: Behold, this day I enter into co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:96187:70"/> with thee, and if thou keepeſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, I will be as a <hi>burning lampe</hi> to illighten and to comfort thee: But if thou breakeſt covenant, I will be like a <hi>ſmoaking furnace</hi> to conſume thee. Thus alſo <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.6. <hi>Moſes</hi> makes a covenant with Iſrael, and offers ſacrifices, &amp; takes the blood of the ſacrifice and divides it, and half of it he ſprinkles upon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, (which repreſented Gods part) and the other half he ſprinkled upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>As this blood is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, ſo will God divide you if you break covenant.</hi> This was the cuſtom amongſt the Jews. Amongſt the Romans, <hi>Caeſa fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabant foedera porca.</hi> And when it was divided, the <hi>Feciales</hi> gave one half to one party, &amp; the other half to the other, and ſaid, <hi>So God divide you aſunder if you break this covenant, and let God do this, ſo much the more by how much he is the more able. Hinc foedus à foedo animali (ſcilicet porco) diviſo.</hi> Sometimes they make co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants by taking a ſtone in their hands and ſaying, <hi>If I make this covenant ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly &amp; faithfully then let the great Iupiter bleſs me. If not, ſo let me be caſt away from the face of the gods as I caſt away this ſtone</hi> This was called <hi>Jurare per Jovem lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</hi> All theſe things are not <hi>empty notions,</hi> and <hi>metaphorical ſhadowes,</hi>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:96187:71"/> but real and ſubſtantial practiſes, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying unto us, That <hi>God will, and muſt</hi> (for it ſtands with his honour to do it) <hi>divide and break them in pieces that break covenant with him.</hi> This day you are to take a Covenant by the lifting up of your hands unto the moſt high God, which is a moſt emphatical ceremony, whereby we doe as it were call God to be a <hi>witneſſe</hi> and a <hi>judge</hi> of what we doe, and a <hi>rewarder</hi> or a <hi>revenger,</hi> according as we keep or break the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. If we keep it, <hi>the lifting up of our hands</hi> will be as an <hi>Evening ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice;</hi> if we break it, <hi>the lifting up of our hands</hi> will be as the <hi>lifting up of the hands of a Malefactor at the Bar,</hi> and procure woe and miſery and <hi>wringing of hands</hi> at the great day of appearing.</p>
            <p>The third reaſon why God will be avenged of thoſe that are Covenant-breakers, is, becauſe that a <hi>Covenant</hi> is the <hi>greateſt obligation,</hi> and the moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible <hi>chain</hi> that can be invented to tye us to obedience and ſervice. <hi>God</hi> may juſtly challenge obedience without <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting</hi> by virtue of <hi>creation, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> and <hi>redemption;</hi> he hath made us, and when loſt, he hath purchaſed us with his blood. But being willing
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:96187:71"/> more abundantly to manifeſt his love, and that we might be the more faſtned to him, he hath tyed himſelf to us, and us to him by the ſtrong bond of a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> as if God ſhould ſay, Oh ye ſons of men, I ſee you are rebellious, and ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> and therefore if it be poſſible, I will make you ſure. I will engage you unto me, not only by <hi>creation, preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> &amp; <hi>redemption,</hi> but alſo by the right of <hi>covenant</hi> and <hi>aſſociation.</hi> I will make you mine by <hi>promiſe</hi> &amp; <hi>oath.</hi> And ſurely he that will break theſe bonds, is as bad as the man poſſeſſed with the <hi>Divel</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> whom no chains could keep faſt. When we enter into covenant with <hi>God,</hi> we take the oath of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and ſwear unto him that he ſhal be our chief <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Governour,</hi> &amp; that we will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit no forein power or juriſdiction, but that God ſhall be all in all. We likewiſe take the oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> to be his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and vaſſals, and that he ſhal be our Supreme in ſpirituals &amp; temporals. Now for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> that believes there is a <hi>God,</hi> to break both theſe oaths of <hi>allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> and <hi>ſupremacy,</hi> it is curſed <hi>treaſon</hi> againſt the <hi>God</hi> of heaven, which ſurely <hi>God</hi> wil be avenged of. Amongſt the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> when any Souldier was preſſed, he
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:96187:72"/> took an oath to ſerve the Captain faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and not to forſake him, and he was called <hi>Miles per ſacramentum.</hi> Sometimes one took an oath for all the reſt, and the others only ſaid, <hi>The ſame oath that A. B. took, the ſame do I.</hi> And theſe were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Milites per conjurationem,</hi> or <hi>milites evocati.</hi> And when any ſouldier forſook his Captain, he had Martial law execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon him. Thus it is with every Chriſtian: He is a profeſſ;ed <hi>ſouldier of Chriſt,</hi> he hath taken preſs-mony, he hath ſworn and taken the <hi>Sacrament</hi> upon it to become the <hi>Lords,</hi> he is <hi>miles per ſacramentum,</hi> &amp; <hi>miles per conjuratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi> And if he forſake his Captain and break covenant, the great <hi>Lord of Hoſts</hi> will be avenged of him, as it is written, <hi>Jer.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Curſed be the main that obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the words of this covenant.</hi> To break covenant is a ſin of <hi>perjury,</hi> which is a ſin of high nature; and if <hi>for oaths the land mourneth,</hi> much more for breach of oaths. To break covenant is a ſin of ſpiritual adultery; for by cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting with God we do as it were <hi>joyn our ſelves in marriage to God,</hi> as the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew word ſignifieth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.5. Now to break the <hi>mariage knot</hi> is a ſin for which God may juſtly give a Bill of divorce to
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:96187:72"/> a Nation. To <hi>break covenant</hi> is a ſin of <hi>injuſtice;</hi> for by our covenant we do enter as it were into <hi>bond</hi> to <hi>God</hi> &amp; engage our ſelves as a creditor to his debtor. Now the ſin of injuſtice is a <hi>land deſtroying ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Reaſon why God muſt needs be avenged of thoſe that are <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-breakers,</hi> is, becauſe it is an act of the higheſt <hi>Sacriledge</hi> that can be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. For by vertue of the Covenant the Lord layes claim to us as his pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar inheritance, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.8. <hi>I ſware unto thee, and entred into covenant with thee, and thou becameſt mine. Jer.</hi> 31.33. <hi>I will be their God and they ſhall be my people.</hi> It is worthy obſervation, that in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant there is a double <hi>ſurrender,</hi> one on <hi>Gods part,</hi> another on our part. God Almighty makes a <hi>ſurrender</hi> of himſelf, and of his <hi>Sonne,</hi> and of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Behold, ſaith <hi>God,</hi> I am wholly thy <hi>God;</hi> all my power, and mercy, and goodneſſe, &amp;c. is all thine, my <hi>Son</hi> is thine, and all his rich purchaſes. My <hi>ſpirit</hi> is thine and all his graces. This is <hi>Gods ſurrender.</hi> On our parts, when we take hold of the Covenant, we make a delivery of our bodies and ſouls into the hands of God, we chooſe him to be our Lord and Governour, we reſign up
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:96187:73"/> our ſelves into his hands. Lord we are thine at thy diſpoſing; we alienate our ſelves from our ſelves, and make a deed of gift of our ſelves, and give thee the lock and key of head, heart, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, &amp;c. This is the nature of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry religious Covenant, but eſpecially of the Covenant of grace. But now for a Chriſtian to call in as it were his <hi>ſurrender,</hi> to diſclaime his <hi>reſignation,</hi> to ſteal away himſelf from God and to lay claim to himſelf after his alienation; to fulfill his own luſts, to walk after his own wayes, to do what he liſts, and not what he hath Covenanted to do, and ſo to rob God of what is his, this is the <hi>higheſt degree of Sacriledge,</hi> which God will never ſuffer to go unpuniſhed. And ſurely if the ſtick-gatherer, that did but alienate a little of Gods time; and <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira,</hi> that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held but ſome part of his eſtate: and if <hi>Belſhazzer</hi> for abuſing the conſecrated veſſels of the Temple were ſo grievouſly puniſhed; how much more will God puniſh thoſe that alienate themſelves from the ſervice of that God whom they have ſworn to be obedient? It is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by a learned Author, of three famous Commanders of the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:96187:73"/> that they never proſpered after they had defiled and robbed the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Pompey</hi> the great, he went into the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> a place never before entred by any but the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> and the Lord blaſted him in all his proceedings after that time. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t illi qui terram non habuit ante ad victoriam, de eſſet illi terra at ſepultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram:</hi> That he that before that time wanted earth to overcome, had not at laſt earth enough to bury him withall. The next was <hi>Craſſus,</hi> who took away 10000 talents of gold from the Temple, and afterwards dyed, by having gold poured down his throat. The third was <hi>Caſſius,</hi> who afterwards killed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. If then God did thus avenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of thoſe that polluted his <hi>conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Temple;</hi> much more will he not leave them unpuniſhed that are the <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving temples</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to God by a <hi>Covenant,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards proving <hi>ſacrilegious,</hi> robbing God of that worſhip and ſervice which they have ſworn to give him.</p>
            <p>The fifth reaſon why this ſin makes the time perilous is, becauſe <hi>covenant-breakers</hi> are reckoned amongſt the number of thoſe that have the <hi>mark</hi> of
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:96187:74"/> 
               <hi>reprobation</hi> upon them. I do not ſay that they are all Reprobates; yet I ſay that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> makes it to be one of thoſe ſins which are committed by thoſe that are given up to a reprobate mind, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28.31. The words are ſpoken of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and are to be underſtood of Covenants made between man and man. But then the Argument will hold <hi>à fortiori.</hi> If it be the brand of a reprobate to break covenant with man, much more a <hi>covenant</hi> made with the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> by the lifting up of our hands to Heaven.</p>
            <p>The laſt reaſon is, becauſe it is a ſin againſt ſuch infinite mercy, ſuch bowels of Gods unexpreſſible mercy. It is ſaid, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.22. <hi>Which covenant they brake, although I was a Husband to them.</hi> That is, although I had choſen them for my Spouſe, and married my ſelf unto them with an everlaſting Covenant of mercy, and intailed heaven unto them, yet they have broken my Covenant. This was a great provocation. Thus <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16 4, 5, <hi>When thou waſt in thy blood and no eye pitied thee to have compaſſion upon thee, I ſaid unto thee when thou wert in thy blood, Live;</hi> yea, <hi>I ſaid unto thee Live.</hi> It is twice repeated. As if God ſhould
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:96187:74"/> ſay, Mark it O Iſrael, when no eye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded thee, then I ſaid unto thee, Live. <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith God, ver. 8. <hi>thy time was the time of Love.</hi> Behold and wonder at it, <hi>and I ſpread my skirt over thee, and covered thy nakedneſſe: yea, I ſware unto thee, and entered into covenant with thee,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and thou becameſt. mine.</hi> And yet for all this thou haſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned grievouſly againſt me. <hi>Woe woe unto thee, ſaith the Lord God, Ezek.</hi> 16.23. There is <hi>fivefold mercy</hi> in the <hi>covenant,</hi> (eſpecially in the covenant of grace) that makes the ſinne of <hi>covenant-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to be ſo odious.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is a mercy that the great <hi>God</hi> will vouchſafe to enter into <hi>covenant</hi> with duſt &amp; aſhes. As <hi>David</hi> ſaith in another caſe, <hi>is it a ſleight matter to be the ſon in law of a King?</hi> ſo may I ſay, is it a ſleight matter for the Lord of heaven &amp; earth to condeſcend ſo far as to <hi>covenant</hi> with his poor creatures, &amp; thereby to become their <hi>debtors,</hi> &amp; to make them as it were his <hi>equals?</hi> When <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>David</hi> entered into a Covenant of friendſhip, though one was a Kings Sonne, the other a poor Shepheard, yet there was then a kind of equality between them. But this muſt be underſtood wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:96187:75"/> according to the the text, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2 9. <hi>Bleſſed be God who hath called us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fellowſhip of his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> He is ſtill our Lord, though in fellowſhip with us. It is a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of infinite condeſcenſion on Gods part, whereby he enters into a league of friendſhip to with his people.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The mercy is the greater, becauſe this <hi>covenant</hi> was made after the fall of <hi>Adam;</hi> after we had broken the firſt covenant. That the Lord ſhould try us the ſecond time, is not only an act of infinite goodneſs of God, but of infinite mercy. There is a difference between the <hi>goodneſſe</hi> and the <hi>mercy</hi> of God. <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> may be ſhewed to thoſe that are not in <hi>miſery:</hi> but <hi>mercy</hi> ſuppoſeth <hi>miſery,</hi> and this was our condition after the breach of the firſt covenant.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That God ſhould make this cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with <hi>Man,</hi> and not with <hi>Devils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. This ſets out the mercy of the <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> becauſe it contains ſuch rare and glorious benefits, and therefore it is called a <hi>covenant of life and peace, Mal.</hi> 2.5. <hi>an everlaſting, covenant even the ſure mercies of David, Eſa.</hi> 54.3. It is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the <hi>waters of Noah, Eſa.</hi> 54.6. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:96187:75"/> are thoſe two Texts, <hi>Exodus</hi> 19.5, 6. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40, 41. Texts that hold forth <hi>ſtrong conſolation.</hi> By vertue of the <hi>covenant,</hi> Heaven is not only made poſſible, but certain to all believers, and certain by way of <hi>oath.</hi> It is by vertue of the <hi>covenant</hi> that we call God <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and may lay claim to all the power, wiſdome, goodneſſe and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, &amp;c. that is in <hi>God.</hi> As <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> told the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to whom he was joyned in covenant, <hi>I am as thou art, my people as thy people, my horſes as thy horſes:</hi> So doth God ſay to all that are in <hi>covenant</hi> with him; <hi>My power is thine, my goodneſſe is thine, &amp;c.</hi> By vettue of this covenant, whatſoever thou wanteſt <hi>God</hi> cannot deny it thee, if it be good for thee. Say unto God, <hi>Lord, thou haſt ſworn to take away my heart of ſtone, end to give me a heart of fleſh. Thou haſt ſworn to write thy law in my heart, thou haſt ſworn to circumciſe my heart, thou haſt ſworn to gave me Chriſt to be my King, Prieſt, and Prophet, &amp;c.</hi> And God cannot but be a <hi>covenant-keeper.</hi> By vertue of this <hi>covenant, God</hi> cannot but accept of a poor penitent ſinner laying hold upon Chriſt for pardon, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Promiſſa haec tua ſunt,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:96187:76"/> Domine; &amp; quis falli timet cum promit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit ipſa veritas?</hi> In a word, we may challenge pardon, and heaven by our Covenant; 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9. God is not only <hi>merciful,</hi> but <hi>juſt</hi> to forgive us. We may challenge Heaven through Chriſt out of juſtice.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Add laſtly, that the conditions of the Covenant on our parts ſhould be upon ſuch eaſie terms, therefore it is called a <hi>covenant</hi> of <hi>Free-grace.</hi> All that God requires of us, is to take hold of this Covenant; <hi>Iſa</hi> 56 <hi>to receive this gift of righteouſneſſe, Rom</hi> 5. to take <hi>all Chriſt</hi> as he is tendred in the Covenant. And that which is the greateſt conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all, God hath promiſed in his Covenant to do our part for us, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33, 34. Therefore it is called a <hi>Teſtament</hi> rather then a Covenant. (In the new Teſtament the wore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is alwaies uſed by the Apoſtle, and not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>Heaven</hi> is conveyed unto the Elect by way of Legacy; It is part of Gods <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> to write his Law in our hearts, and to cauſe us to walk in his wayes, &amp;c. Put theſe things together. Seeing there is ſuch infinite mercy in the Covenant. A mercy for <hi>God to enter into covenant with us, to do it with us and not the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:96187:76"/> with us fallen, with us upon ſuch eaſie termes; and to make ſuch a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that containes ſo many, and not onely ſo, but all bleſſings here and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the wombe of it;</hi> it muſt needs be a land-deſtroying, and ſoul-deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſin to a <hi>Covenant-breaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The uſe and application of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is four-fold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. <hi>Of information.</hi> If it be ſuch a <hi>Land-devouring ſin</hi> to be a <hi>Covenant-breaker,</hi> let us from hence learn the <hi>true cauſe</hi> of all the miſeries that have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto <hi>England</hi> in theſe late yeares. The <hi>wombe</hi> out of which all our cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities are come. <hi>England</hi> hath broken <hi>Covenant</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> and now <hi>God</hi> is breaking <hi>England</hi> in pieces, even as a Potter breakes a veſſel in pieces. <hi>God hath ſent his ſword to avenge the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of his Covenant.</hi> As Chriſt whipt the buyers and ſellers out of the Temple, with whips made of the cords which they brought to tye their oxen and, ſheep withall. A <hi>Covenant</hi> is a cord to tye us to God, and now <hi>God</hi> hath made an iron whip of theſe cords which we have broken aſunder to whip us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
            <p>We are a Nation in <hi>Covenant with
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:96187:77"/> God,</hi> we have the <hi>books of the covenant,</hi> the Old and New Teſtament; we have the <hi>ſeales of the covenant,</hi> Baptiſme and the Lords Supper. We have the <hi>Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the covenant,</hi> the Miniſters of the Goſpel. We have the <hi>Angells of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> the Lord Jeſus Chriſt fully and clearly ſet out before us in the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the word. But alas, are not theſe bleſſings amongſt us, as the Ark was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> rather as <hi>priſoners</hi> then as <hi>priviledges;</hi> rather <hi>in teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium &amp; ruinam quam in ſalutem,</hi> rather for our ruine then for our happineſſe? May it not be ſaid of us, as Reverend <hi>Moulin</hi> ſaid of the French Proteſtants; <hi>While they burned us</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, we burnt with zeal to be reading of them: now with our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is bred alſo negligence and diſeſteem of Gods word?</hi> So is it with us. While we were under the <hi>Tyranny of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> oh how ſweet was a <hi>Faſting-day!</hi> how <hi>beautifull were the feet of them that brought the Goſpel of peace unto you?</hi> How dear and precious were Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple one to another, &amp;c. But now how are our Faſting-days ſleighted and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified? how are the people of God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided one from another, railing upon
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:96187:77"/> (inſtead of loving) one another? And is not the <hi>godly Miniſtery</hi> as much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by the tongues of ſome that would be accounted godly, as heretofore by the Biſhops hand? Is not the <hi>Holy Bible</hi> by ſome rather <hi>wreſted</hi> then <hi>read?</hi> wreſted I ſay by ignorant and unſtable ſouls, to their own deſtruction. And us for the <hi>ſeals of the covenant.</hi> 1. For the <hi>Lords Supper;</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w often have we ſpilt the <hi>blood of Chriſt</hi> by our unworthy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to his Table? and hence it is that he is now ſpilling our blood. How hard a matter is it to obtain power to keep the blood of Chriſt from being profaned by ignorant and ſcandalous Communicants? and can we think that God will be eaſily intreated to ſheath up his bloody ſword, and to ceaſe ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our blood? 2. For the <hi>Sacrament of Baptiſme;</hi> how cruel are men grown to their <hi>little infants,</hi> by keeping of them from the ſeal of entrance into the <hi>Kingdome of heaven,</hi> and making their children (their own children) to be juſt in the ſame condition with the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Turks and Infidels?</hi> I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at the beginning of theſe Wars, there was a great fear fell upon godly people about their little children, and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:96187:78"/> all their care was for the preſervation, and their ſafety; and for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Goſpel to them &amp;c. But now our little children are likely to be in a worſer condition then ever. And all this is come upon us as a juſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our <hi>Baptiſmall covenant-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> And as for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> who is the <hi>Angell</hi> of the <hi>covenant:</hi> are there not ſome amongſt us that <hi>un-god Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> and is it not fit and equal that God ſhould <hi>un-church</hi> us, and <hi>un-peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> us? are there not thouſands that have ſworn to be <hi>Chriſts ſervants,</hi> and yet are in their lives the <hi>Vaſſals of ſinne and ſatan?</hi> and ſhall not God be aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of ſuch a nation as this? theſe things conſidered, is no wonder our miſeries are ſo great, but the wonder is, that they are no greater.</p>
            <p>The 2d. uſe, is an uſe of examination.</p>
            <p>Days of <hi>humiliation</hi> ought to be days of <hi>ſelf-examination.</hi> Let us therefore up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a day as this, examine whether we be not amongſt the number of thoſe that make the times perilous, whether we be not <hi>covenant-breakers?</hi> Here I will ſpeak of three Covenants: 1. Of the <hi>covenant we made with God in our Baptiſme.</hi> 2. Of <hi>the covenant we have
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:96187:78"/> made with God in our diſtreſſes.</hi> Thirdly, and eſpecially of this <hi>covenant you are to renue this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, of the <hi>covenant</hi> which we made in <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and renue every time we come to the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> and upon our ſolemn days of faſting. There are none here, but I may ſay of them, The <hi>vows of God are upon you.</hi> You are <hi>ſervi nati, empti, jurati,;</hi> you are the <hi>born, bought,</hi> and <hi>ſworn ſervants</hi> of God, you have made a <hi>ſurrender</hi> of your ſelves unto <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The queſtion I put to you is this: how often have you <hi>broke covenant with God?</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.14. <hi>The ſinners of Sion are afraid: who ſhall dwell with everlaſting torments? who ſhall dwel with devouring fire</hi> &amp;c. When God comes to a <hi>Church-ſinner,</hi> to a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner under the Old Teſtament, much more to a <hi>Chriſtian ſinner;</hi> a ſinner un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>new Teſtament:</hi> and layeth to his charge his often <hi>covenant-breaking fear fulneſs ſhall poſſeſs</hi> him, and he will cry out, oh! wo is me, <hi>who can dwel with ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting burnings?</hi> our <hi>God</hi> is a <hi>conſuming fire,</hi> and we are as <hi>ſtubble</hi> before him. <hi>Who can ſtund before his indignation?</hi> (Nah. 1.6.) <hi>who can abide in the fierceneſs of his anger? when his fury is poured forth
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:96187:79"/> like fire, and the rocks are thrown down before him.</hi> Who can ſtand? of all ſorts of creatures, a ſinful Chriſtian ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able to ſtand before the Lord, when he comes to viſit the world for their ſins. For when a Chriſtian ſinnes againſt God, he ſins not only againſt the <hi>commandement,</hi> but againſt the <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi> And in every ſin he is a <hi>comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement-breaker</hi> and a <hi>covenant-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> And therefore whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Tribulation and anguiſh upon every ſoul that ſinneth, but firſt upon the Jew,</hi> &amp;c. I may add; Firſt upon the <hi>chriſtian,</hi> then upon the <hi>Jew,</hi> and then upon the <hi>Grecian;</hi> becauſe the Covenant made with the Chriſtian is called a <hi>better co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant;</hi> and therefore his ſins hath a higher aggravation in them. There is a notable paſſage in <hi>Auſtin,</hi> in which he brings the devil thus pleading with God againſt a wicked chriſtian at the day of judgement. <hi>Aequiſſime judex, judica quod aequum eſt, judica meum eſſe qui tuus eſſe noluit poſt renunciationem; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſit pannos meos? Quid apud eum laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civia, incontinentia, &amp;c. quibus ipſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciaverit? Quid intemperantia, quid gula, quid faſtus, quid caetera mea? Haec omnia mea poſt renunciationem invaſit.
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:96187:79"/> Meus eſſe voluit, mea concupivit; Judica, aequiſſime judex, quoniam quam tu non dedignatus es tanto pretio liberare, ipſe mihi poſtmodum voluit obligare.</hi> That is, Oh thou righteous Judge, give right judgement! Judge him to be mine, who refuſed to be thine even after he had renounced me in his Baptiſme; What had he to do to wear my Livery? What had he to doe with gluttony, drunkenneſs, pride, wantonneſs, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency; and the reſt of my ware? All theſe things he hath practiſed ſince he recounced the Devil and all his works. Mine he is, judge righteous judgement; For he whom thou haſt not diſdained to dye for, hath obliged himſelf to me by his ſins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what can God ſay to this charge of the Devils, but, <hi>take him Devil,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he would be thine, take him, <hi>torment</hi> him with <hi>everlaſting torments? Cyprian</hi> brings in the Devil thus ſpeaking to Chriſt at the great day of judgement, <hi>Ego pro iſtis quos mecum vides nec alapas accepi, nec flagella ſuſtinui, nec crucem pertuli, nec ſanguinem fudi, ſed nec reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num coeleſte illis promitto, nec ad para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſum evoco &amp; tamen ſe mihi ſua<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia conſecrarunt.</hi> I have not ſaid (ſaith
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:96187:80"/> the Devil) been whipt and ſcourged, and crucified, neither have I ſhed my blood for theſe whom thou ſeeſt with me. I do not promiſe them a kingdom of Heaven, &amp;c. And yet theſe men have wholy conſecrated themſelves to me &amp; my ſervice. Indeed if the Devil could make ſuch gainful covenants with us, and beſtow ſuch glorious mercies upon us as are contained within the covenant, our ſerving of Satan and ſin might have ſome excuſe. But when as his <hi>covenant</hi> is a <hi>covenant</hi> bondage, death, hell, and damnation: and <hi>Gods covenant</hi> is a <hi>covenant</hi> of liberty, grace, and eternall happineſs, it muſt needs be a ſin inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, to be willing and wilfully ſuch a covenant-breaker.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us examine concerning the <hi>vowes</hi> which we have made to God in our <hi>diſtreſſes:</hi> in our perſonal diſtreſſes, and our National diſtreſſes. Are we not like the children ef <hi>Iſrael</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78 34. <hi>When he ſlew them, then they ſought him, and they returned and enquired early after God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Nevertheleſs they did but flatter him with their mouth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For their heart was not right with him, neither were they ſtedfaſt in his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant?</hi> Are we not like unto little
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:96187:80"/> children, that while they are whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping will promiſe any thing, but when the whipping is over will performe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? Or like unto Iron that is very ſoft and malleable while it is in the fire, but when it is taken out of the fire, returns preſently to his former hardneſſe? This was <hi>Jacobs</hi> fault: He made a <hi>vow</hi> when he was in diſtreſſe <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.22. But he forgat his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and God was angry with him, and chaſtiſed him in his Daughter <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah, Gen.</hi> 34.5. &amp; in his two ſons <hi>Simeon and Levi.</hi> And at laſt God himſelf was fain to call to him from heaven to keep covenant. And after that time God bleſſed <hi>Jacob</hi> exceedingly, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.9, 10, 11, 12. We read of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 56.13, 14, 15. that he profeſſeth of himſelf, that he <hi>would go into Gods houſe, and pay the vows which his lips had uttered, and his mouth had ſpoken when he was in trouble.</hi> But how few are there that i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate <hi>David</hi> in this thing?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us examine our ſelves concerning ihis ſolemne League and Covenant which we are to renue this day. And here I demand an anſwer to this queſtion.</p>
            <pb n="154" facs="tcp:96187:81"/>
            <p>Q. Are we not <hi>covenant-breakers?</hi> do we not make the times perilous by our falſifying of our oath and <hi>covenant with God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In our Covenant we ſwear to ſix things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That we will <hi>endeavour</hi> to be <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for our ſins and for the ſins of the kingdome.</hi> But where ſhall we find a <hi>mourner in England</hi> for his own abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations that are committed in the midſt of us? it is eaſie to find a <hi>cenſurer</hi> of the ſins of the Land, but hard to find a true mourner for the ſins of the land.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We ſwear <hi>that we will endeavour to go before one another in the example of a reall reformation.</hi> But who makes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of this part of the Oath? What ſin haſt thou left, or in what one thing haſt thou been reformed ſince thou tookeſt this Covenant? We read, <hi>Ezra.</hi> 10.7. <hi>That they entered into covenant, to put away their wives and their children by them:</hi> which was a very difficult and hard duty and yet did they it. But what boſome ſin, what beloved ſin, as dear to thee as thy dear wife and children, haſt thou left for Gods ſake ſince thou took<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt this Oath? I read <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.13. that the people took an Oath to make <hi>reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,</hi>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:96187:81"/> which was a coſtly duty, and yet they performed it, ſaith the Text. But alas! where is the man that hath made reſtitution of his ill gotten goods ſince he took this Covenant? I read 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.16. that King <hi>Aſa</hi> depoſed his Mother <hi>Maachah, her, even her, from being Queen,</hi> after he had entered into Covenant: and that the people, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 11.18. after they had ſworn a <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, brake in pieces all the Altars of Baall thoroughly.</hi> But where is this <hi>thorough Reformation,</hi> this <hi>thorough</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life? Indeed here is much talk of a <hi>Reformation,</hi> but little practice of a <hi>Reformation.</hi> We ſay we <hi>fight</hi> for a <hi>Reformation;</hi> but I fear leſt in a little time we ſhould <hi>fight</hi> away our <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation:</hi> or if not <hi>fight</hi> it away, yet we ſhould diſpute it away. For now all our religion is turned into <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum</hi>'s, into <hi>Queſtions,</hi> inſomuch as that there are ſome that call all <hi>religion</hi> into queſtion, and in a little while will looſe all <hi>reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> in the crowd of <hi>queſtions. Inter disputandum veritas, &amp; religio amittitur.</hi> There was a time not many years agoe, when God did bleſſe our Miniſtery in the City, to the <hi>converſion</hi> of many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto God; but now there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:96187:82"/> that ſtudy more to <hi>gain parties</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, then to gain ſouls to God. The great work of <hi>converſion</hi> is little thought on. And ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo few (if any at all) converted as in theſe days wherein we talk ſo much of <hi>Reformation.</hi> And is this to keep Covenant with God?</p>
            <p n="3">3. We ſwear <hi>to endeavour to amend the lives, and reform not only our ſelves, but alſo thoſe that are under our charge.</hi> But where is this Family-reformation? indeed I read of <hi>Jacob,</hi> that when he went to perform his vow and covenant, he firſt reformed his family, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.3 And that <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> reſolved (and per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ormed it) <hi>for himſelf and his family to ſerve the Lord.</hi> And ſo did <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h that I could add, <hi>And ſo do we!</hi> but the wickedneſſes committed in our families, proclaim the contrary to all the world. What <hi>Noblemans,</hi> what <hi>Aldermans,</hi> what <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> family is more reformed ſince the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n before? we ſpeak and contend much for a <hi>Church-reformation;</hi> but how can there be a <hi>Church-reformation,</hi> unleſs there be a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily-reformation?</hi> What though the <hi>Church-worſhip</hi> be pure, yet if the <hi>worſhippers</hi> be impure, God will not accept of the <hi>worſhip?</hi> And if fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies be not reformed, how will your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers be pure.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We ſwear <hi>to endeavour to bring the Churches of God in the three Kingdoms, to the near<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt conjunction and uniformity in Religion, confeſſion of Faith, form of Church-government, Directory for worſhip and catechizing,</hi> &amp;c. But are there not ſome that write againſt an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and call it an <hi>Idoll?</hi> Are there not many that walk profeſſedly contrary to this clauſe of the <hi>covenant?</hi> There are three Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that people keep the quite contrary way.
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:96187:82"/> The firſt is <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.34, 31, 25. <hi>Take no thought what you ſhall eat, &amp;c. take no thought for to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> And moſt people take thought for nothing elſe. The ſecond text is <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. <hi>Seek ye firſt the kingdome of God and his righteouſneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. And moſt people ſeek this laſt of all. The third text is, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.27. <hi>Labour not for the meat that periſheth, but for the meat that endureth for ever,</hi> &amp;c. And moſt people labour not for the meat that endureth for ever, but for the meat that periſheth. As theſe three texts are kept, ſo do many people keep this part of the Oath; for there were never more <hi>diviſions</hi> and <hi>differences</hi> in the Church, never more <hi>difformity,</hi> and plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt <hi>uniformity,</hi> then now there is.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We ſwear <hi>to endeavour the extirpation of Popery, Prelacy, Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſme,</hi> &amp;c. And yet notwithſtanding there are ſome that have taken this Oath, that contend earneſtly for a Toleration of all Religions.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>We ſwear againſt a deteſtable indifferency and Neutrality in this cauſe which ſo much concerneth the glory of God,</hi> &amp;c. And yet how many are there amongſt us that are like unto <hi>Gallio,</hi> that care not what becomes of the <hi>cauſe of God,</hi> ſo they may have peace and quiet? That will not be the <hi>backwardeſt</hi> of all, and yet will be ſure not to be too <hi>forward,</hi> for fear leſt if the times turn, they ſhould be noted amongſt the chief of the <hi>Faction?</hi> That are very indifferent which ſide prevail, ſo they may have their trading a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? That ſay as the <hi>Polititian, that they would be carefull not to come to near the heels of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leſt it ſhould daſh out its brains:</hi> And as the King of <hi>Arragon</hi> told <hi>Beza, that he would wade no further into the ſea of Religion then he could ſafely return to ſhoar?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="158" facs="tcp:96187:83"/>
            <p>In all theſe ſix particulars let us ſeriouſly ſearch and try our hearts, whether we be not a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongſt the number of thoſe that make the times perilous.</p>
            <p>The third uſe is for <hi>Humiliation.</hi> Let the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of our <hi>Covenant-breaking,</hi> be a <hi>heart-breaking</hi> conſideration to every one of us this day. Let this be a mighty and powerful Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bumble us upon this day of humiliation.</p>
            <p>There are five conſiderations that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly <hi>ſoul-humbling,</hi> if God bleſs them unto us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The conſideration of the many <hi>commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of God that we have often &amp; often broken</p>
            <p n="2">2. The conſideration of the breaking of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> for our ſins, how he was rent and torn for our iniquities.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The conſideration of the <hi>breaking of the bread,</hi> and the <hi>pouring</hi> out of the <hi>wine</hi> in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, which is a heart-breaking motive and help.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>broken condition</hi> that the <hi>Kingdome of England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> is in at this time.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The many <hi>Vowes and Covenants</hi> that we have broken; our <hi>Sacrament-covenants,</hi> our <hi>Faſting-covenants,</hi> our <hi>Sick bed-Covenants.</hi> And eſpecially the conſideration of our often break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our <hi>Nationall-covenant</hi> which you come this day to renue. This is a ſin in <hi>Folio,</hi> a ſin of a <hi>high nature:</hi> and if ever God awaken conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in this life, a ſin that will lye like a heavy <hi>Incuba</hi> upon it. A greater ſin then a ſin againſt a <hi>Commandement,</hi> or againſt an <hi>Ordinance.</hi> A ſin not only of <hi>diſobedience,</hi> but of <hi>perjury.</hi> A ſin of <hi>injuſtice,</hi> of <hi>ſpiritual Adultery.</hi> A ſin of <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> A ſin of great <hi>unkindneſſe.</hi> A ſin
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:96187:83"/> that makes us not only diſobedient, but diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. For we account him a diſhoneſt man that keeps not his word. A ſin that not only every good <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> but every good <hi>Heathen</hi> doth abhor. A ſin, that not onely brings <hi>Damnation</hi> upon us, but caſteth ſuch into horrible <hi>diſgrace and reproach upon God,</hi> that it cannot ſtand with Gods honour not to be avenged of a <hi>Covenant-breaker. Tertullian</hi> ſaith, that when a Chriſtian forſakes his Covenant, and the colours of Chriſt, and turnes to ſerve as the Divels ſouldier, he puts an unſpeakable diſcredit upon God and Chriſt. For it is as much as if he ſhould ſay; <hi>I like the ſervice of the Divel better then the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God.</hi> And it is juſt as if a ſouldier that hath waged war under a <hi>Captain,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards forſaking him turnes to another, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that leaves this other Captain and returns to his former Captain. This is to prefer the firſt Captain before the ſecond. This makes God complain, <hi>Jer.</hi> 24. <hi>What iniquity have your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers found in me that they are gone far from me,</hi> &amp;c. And in the 11 ver. <hi>Hath any Nation chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their God, which are yet no Gods? but my people have changed their glory for that which doth not profit. Baſill</hi> brings in the Devil inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over Chriſt, and ſaying, I <hi>never created nor redeemed theſe men, and yet they have obeyed me, contemned thee, O Chriſt, even after they have Covenanted to be thine</hi> And then he addes <hi>Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ego iſtam futuram adverſus Chriſtum gloriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem hoſtis inſolentem gravius longe eſſe ſtatuo quam Geheimae ſupplicia.</hi> That is, <hi>I eſteem this inſulting of the Devill over Jeſus Chriſt at the great day, to be more grievous to a true Saint, then all the torments of hell.</hi> A ſaying worthy to be written in letters of gold. Seeing then that
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:96187:84"/> 
               <hi>covenant-breaking</hi> is ſo great an abomination, the Lord give us hearts to be humbled for this great abomination this day. And this will be a notable preparation to ſit you to the renuing of your Covenant. For we read that <hi>Nehemiah</hi> firſt called his people to faſt, before he drew them into a Covenant. According to which pattern you are here met to pray, and humble your ſoules for your former <hi>covenant-breaking;</hi> and then to bind your ſelves anew unto the <hi>Lord our God.</hi> As <hi>wax</hi> when it is melted will receive the impreſſion of a ſeal, which it will not do before: ſo will your hearts, when <hi>mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> into <hi>godly ſorrow</hi> for our ſins, receive the <hi>ſeal</hi> of God abidingly upon them, which they will not do when hardned in ſin.</p>
            <p>Is every man that ſins againſt the <hi>covenant</hi> to be accounted a <hi>covenant-breaker,</hi> and a <hi>perjured ſacrilegious</hi> perſon?</p>
            <p>By no means. For as every <hi>failing</hi> of a <hi>Wife</hi> doth not break a Covenant between her and her Husband; but ſhe is to be accounted a Wife till ſhe by committing adultery break the Covenant. So every miſcariage againſt the <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace,</hi> or againſt this <hi>National-cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> doth not denominate us in a <hi>Goſpell-ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count covenant-breakers.</hi> But then God accounts us according to his Goſpel to break Covenant, when we do not only ſin, but <hi>commit ſin</hi> againſt the Covenant, when we do not only ſin out of <hi>weakneſſe,</hi> but out of <hi>wickedneſſe;</hi> when we do not only <hi>faile,</hi> but fall into ſin; when we <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake</hi> and <hi>renounce</hi> the Covenant, when we deal <hi>treacherouſly in the</hi> Covenant, and enter into <hi>League</hi> and <hi>covenant</hi> with thoſe ſins which we have ſworn againſt. When we walk into <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-covenant</hi> paths, and willingly do contrary to
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:96187:84"/> what we ſwear: then are we perjured and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, and ſacrilegious, and guilty of all theſe things formerly mentioned.</p>
            <p>The fourth Uſe preſents unto you a <hi>Divine,</hi> and therefore a <hi>ſure project</hi> to make the times happy. And that is, <hi>Let all Covenant-takers la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be covenant-keepers.</hi> It hath pleaſed God to put it in your hearts to renue your Covenant. The ſame God inable you to keep Covenant It is ſaid, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34 31, 32. <hi>The King made a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant before the Lord, &amp;c. And he cauſed all that were preſent in Jeruſalem and Benjamin to ſtand to it.</hi> And 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.3. <hi>The King ſtood by a pillar and made a covenant before the Lord, &amp;c. and all the people ſtood to the covenant.</hi> This is your duty, not only to <hi>take the covenant,</hi> but to <hi>ſtand to the covenant;</hi> and to <hi>ſtand</hi> to it, <hi>maugre</hi> all oppoſition to the contrary. According as we read, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.12, 13. <hi>And they entred into covenant to ſeek the Lord God of their fathers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That whoſoever would not ſeek the Lord God of Iſrael, ſhould be put to death, whether ſmall or great, whether man or woman.</hi> For it is not the <hi>taking,</hi> but the <hi>keeping</hi> of the Covenant that will make you happy. God is ſtiled, <hi>A God keeping covenant, Deut.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.5. O that this might be the honour of this City! That we may ſay of it, <hi>London is a City keeping covenant with God.</hi> Great and many are the bleſſings en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailed upon <hi>Covenant-keepers. Exod,</hi> 19.5, 6. <hi>Now therefore if you will obey my voice indeed, and keep my covenant, then you ſhall be a peculiar treaſure unto me above all people: for all the earth is mine: And ye ſhal be unto me a Kingdom of Prieſts, &amp; an holy Nation, &amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 25.10. <hi>All the paths of the Lord, are mercy and truth unto ſuch as keep his covenant, &amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 15.4.</p>
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:96187:85"/>
            <p>There are <hi>three Covenants</hi> I ſhall perſwade you in an eſpecial manner to ſtand to.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The covenant you made with God in Baptiſm.</hi> A Chriſtian (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>) ſhould never <hi>ſtep out of doors,</hi> or <hi>lie down in his bed,</hi> or <hi>go into his cloſet,</hi> but he ſhould remember that word <hi>Abre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuncio;</hi> that is, <hi>He ſhould remember the time when he did renounce the Divel and all his works.</hi> Oh let us not forget that which we ought alwayes to remember! Let us remember to keep that Covenant, as ever we deſire God ſhould remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber us in mercy at the great day.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The covenants which we make unto God in our afflictions.</hi> Famous is that paſſage of <hi>Pliny</hi> in one of his Epiſtles to one that deſired rules from him how to order his life aright. I will (ſaith he) give you one rule which ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a thouſand; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t tales eſſe perſeveremus ſani, quales nos futuros eſſe profitemur infirmi. That we ſhould perſevere to be ſuch when we are well, as we promiſe to be when we are ſick.</hi> A ſentence never to be forgotten. The Lord help us to live accordingly.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The covenant which you are to take this day.</hi> The happineſſe or miſery of <hi>England</hi> doth much depend upon the keeping or breaking of this Covenant. If <hi>England</hi> keep it, <hi>England by keeping covenant ſhall ſtand ſure,</hi> according to that text, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.14. If <hi>England</hi> break it, God will break <hi>England</hi> in pieces. If <hi>England</hi> ſleight it, God will ſleight <hi>England.</hi> If <hi>England</hi> forſake it, God will forſake <hi>England.</hi> And this ſhall be written upon the <hi>Tombe</hi> of periſhing <hi>England: Here lyeth a Nation that hath broken the covenant of their God.</hi> Remember what you have heard this day. That it is the <hi>brand of a Reprobate</hi> to be a Covenant-breaker, &amp;c. It is the part of a <hi>Fool</hi> to <hi>vow,</hi> and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:96187:85"/> not to <hi>pay his vowes.</hi> And <hi>God hath no delight in the ſacrifice of fools. Better not vow, then to vow and not to pay, Eccl.</hi> 5.4, 5. It is ſuch an high prophanation of Gods Name, as that God cannot hold a <hi>Covenant-breaker</hi> guiltleſſe. It is <hi>perjury, injuſtice, ſpiritual adultery, ſacriledge, &amp;c.</hi> And the very <hi>lifting up</hi> of our hands this day (if you do not ſet heart and hand on work to keep co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant) <hi>will be ſufficient witneſs againſt you at the great day.</hi> We read, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.44, 45, 46, 48, 49, 52, 53. <hi>That Jacob and Laban entred into a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ook a heap of ſtones, and made them a witneſſe, and ſaid, This heap is a witneſſe, &amp;c. And they called the name of the place Mizpah: The Lord watch between me and thee, &amp;c. The God of Abraham judge betwixt us, &amp;c.</hi> Such as your condition this day. You enter into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to become the <hi>Lords,</hi> and to be valiant for his truth, and againſt his enemies. And the very <hi>ſtones</hi> of this <hi>Church</hi> ſhall be witneſſe againſt you, if you <hi>break covenant.</hi> The name of this place may be called <hi>Mizpah.</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> will <hi>watch</hi> over you for good, if you keep it, and for evil, if you break it. And all the curſes contained in the book of the Covenant ſhall light upon a willing <hi>covenant-breaker.</hi> The Lord faſten theſe meditations and ſoul-awaking conſiderations upon your hearts. The Lord give you grace to keep cloſe to the Covenant; and in keeping of it to <hi>keep God</hi> and a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> which are both loſt by <hi>covenant-breaking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are 4. things which I ſhall perſwade you unto in purſuance of your Covenant.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To be humbled for your own ſins, and for the ſins of the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngdome; and more eſpecially, <hi>Becauſe we have not as we ought valued the ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable benefit of the Goſpel, that we have not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:96187:86"/> to receive Chriſt in our hearts, nor to walk worthy of him in our lives, which are the cauſes of other ſins and tranſgreſſions ſo much abounding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us. Goſpel-ſins</hi> are greater then <hi>legall ſins,</hi> and will bring <hi>Goſpel-curſes,</hi> which are greater then <hi>legall-curſes.</hi> And therefore let us be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled according to our Covenant for all our <hi>Goſpel abominations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. You muſt be ambitious to <hi>go before one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in an example of real reformation.</hi> You muſt ſwear vainly no more, be drunk no more, break the Sabbath no more, &amp;c. You muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16. <hi>But unto the wicked God ſaith, What haſt thou to do to take my covenant in thy mouth? ſeeing thou hateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and caſteſt my words behind thee.</hi> To ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> willingly after we have ſworn not to ſin, is not only to ſin againſt a <hi>Commandement,</hi> (as I have ſaid) but to ſin againſt an <hi>Oath;</hi> which is a <hi>double iniquity,</hi> and will procure a <hi>double damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And he that takes a Covenant to reform, and yet continued unreformed, his Covenant <hi>will be unto him as the bitter water of jealouſie was to the woman guilty of adultery, which made her belly to ſwell and thigh to rot, &amp;c. Numb.</hi> 5.22.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You muſt be careful <hi>to reform your families according to your covenant,</hi> &amp; the example of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua,</hi> &amp; <hi>Jacob,</hi> &amp; the godly Kings forementioned.</p>
            <p n="4">4 You muſt endeavour <hi>according to your places and callings to bring the churches of God in the three Kingdomes to the neareſt conjunction and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in religion, &amp;c.</hi> O bleſſed <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity!</hi> how come it to paſſe that thou art ſo much ſleighted and contemned? Was not unity one of the chief parts of <hi>Chriſts prayer</hi> unto his <hi>Father</hi> when he was here upon earth? <hi>John</hi> 17.11. Is not <hi>unity</hi> amongſt <hi>Chriſtians</hi> one of the ſtrongeſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:96187:86"/> to perſwade the <hi>world to believe in Chriſt. John</hi> 17.21. Is it not the chief deſire of the <hi>holy Apoſtles,</hi> that we <hi>ſhould all ſpeak the ſame things, and that their ſhould be no diviſions amongſt us,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Is not <hi>unity the happineſs of heaven?</hi> Is it not the happineſſe of a City to be at <hi>unity within it ſelf?</hi> Is it not a <hi>good and pleaſant thing for brethren to dwell together in unity?</hi> how comes it then to paſſe that this part of the Covenant is ſo much forgotten? The Lord mind you of it this day! And the Lord make this great and famous City <hi>a City of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and a City at <hi>unity within it ſelf!</hi> For if <hi>unity</hi> be deſtroyed, <hi>purity</hi> wil quickly alſo be deſtroyd. The Church of God is <hi>una</hi> as well as <hi>ſancta.</hi> It is but <hi>one church</hi> as well as it is a <hi>holy church.</hi> And <hi>Jeſus Chriſt gave ſome to be Apoſtles, &amp;c. till we all come to the unity of the faith.</hi> The goyernment of Chriſt is appointed for the keeping of his Church in <hi>unity</hi> as well as <hi>purity.</hi> Thoſe things which God hath joined together, let no man put aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. That government which doth not promote <hi>unity</hi> as well as <hi>purity,</hi> is not the government of Chriſt. Oh the miſery of that Kingdome where Church-diviſions are nouriſhed and fomented! <hi>A kingdome or a church, divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand.</hi> Would it not be a ſad thing to ſee twelve in a family, &amp; one of them a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> another an <hi>Independent,</hi> another a <hi>Browniſt,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an <hi>Antinomian,</hi> another an <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <hi>Familiſt,</hi> another for the <hi>Prelatical</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, another a <hi>Seeker,</hi> another a <hi>Papiſt</hi> and the tenth it may be an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> the eleventh a <hi>Iew</hi> &amp; the twelth a <hi>Turk?</hi> The Lord in his due time heal our diviſions, and make you his choice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments according to your places, that the <hi>Lord may be one, and his Name one in the three Kingdomes!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:96187:87"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> But ſome will ſay, How ſhall I do to get up my heart to this high pitch that I may be a Covenant-keeper?</p>
            <p>I will propound theſe three helps.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Labour to be <hi>always mindful of your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> according to that text, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.16. <hi>God is always mindful of his Covenant.</hi> It was the great ſin of the people of Iſrael, that they were <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindful</hi> of the Covenant, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.17. They firſt forgat the Covenant, and afterwards did quickly <hi>forſake it.</hi> He that forgets the Covenant, muſt needs be a Covenant-breaker. Let us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore remember it, and carry it about us as <hi>quotidianum argumentum,</hi> and <hi>quotidianum munimentum.</hi> Firſt, let us make a Covenant a <hi>daily argument</hi> aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſt all ſin and iniquity, and when we are tempted to any ſin, let us ſay, <hi>I have ſworn to forſake my old iniquities:</hi> and if I <hi>commit this ſin,</hi> I am not only a Commandment-breaker, but an Oath-breaker; I am <hi>perjur'd,</hi> I have ſworn to <hi>reform my fami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> and therefore I will not ſuffer a <hi>wicked perſon</hi> to tarry in my <hi>family</hi> I have ſworn againſt <hi>neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> and <hi>indifferency,</hi> and therefore I will be <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in Gods cauſe, &amp;c.</hi> Secondly, let us make this Covenant a <hi>daily muniment,</hi> &amp; <hi>armour of defence,</hi> to beat back all the fiery darts of the divel. When any one tempts thee to promiſe of preferment to do contrary to thy Covenant, or by threatning to ruine thee for the hearty purſuing of thy Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, here is a <hi>ready anſwer; I am ſworn to do what I do,</hi> and if I do otherwiſe, I am a <hi>perjur'd wretch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a wall of braſs to reſiſt any dart that ſhall be ſhot againſt thee for well doing accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy Covenant. Famous is the ſtory of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> which he told to King <hi>Antiochus,</hi> when he required aid of him againſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans. <hi>When I was nine years old</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>my
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:96187:87"/> Father carried me to the Altur, and made me take an Oath to be an irreconcileable foe to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans. In purſuance of this Oath, I have waged war againſt them</hi> 36 <hi>years. To keep this Oath I have left my countrey, and am come to ſeek aid at your hands, which if you deny, I will travell all over the world to find out ſome enemies to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſtate. Odi, odio<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſum Romanis.</hi> If an Oath did ſo mightily operate in <hi>Hannibal,</hi> let the Oath you are to take this day, work as power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful upon you; and make your Oath an <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to oppoſe perſonal ſins, and family ſins, and to oppoſe <hi>Hereſie, Schiſme,</hi> and <hi>all profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and to endeavour to <hi>bring the Churches of God in the three Kingdomes to the neareſt conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and uniformity,</hi> &amp;c. And let this Oath be <hi>armour of proof</hi> againſt all temptations to the contrary. And know this one thing, that if the Covenant be not a daily argument and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niment againſt ſin, it will be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome upon your breaking of it, <hi>quotidianum teſtimonium, &amp; aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num opprobrium. A daily witneſſe</hi> againſt you, as the book of the law was, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.26. and an <hi>everlaſting ſhame &amp; reproach</hi> unto you &amp; yours.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us have <hi>high thoughts of the Covenant.</hi> Actions, and affections follow our apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. If thy judgement be <hi>beleapred</hi> with a corrupt opinion about the Covenant, thy affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and actions will quickly be <hi>beleapred alſo.</hi> And therefore you ought to endeavour accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your places, that nothing be ſpoken, or written, that may tend to the <hi>prejudice of the covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. You muſt take heed of the <hi>curſed ſinne of ſelf-love,</hi> which is placed in the <hi>fore-front</hi> as the cauſe of all the Catalogue of ſins here na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; <hi>becauſe men ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of themſelves,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:96187:88"/> they are covetous, &amp;c. and therefore they are <hi>covenant-breakers.</hi> A <hi>ſelf-ſeeker</hi> cannot be a <hi>covenant-breaker;</hi> this is a ſin that you muſt hate as the very gates of hell.</p>
            <p>And this is the <hi>ſecond ſin</hi> that I promiſed in the beginning of my Sermon to ſpeak on: but the time and your other occaſions will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. There is a <hi>natural ſelf-love,</hi> and a <hi>divine ſelf-love,</hi> and a <hi>ſinful ſelf-love.</hi> This <hi>ſinful ſelf-love</hi> is when we make our ſelves the laſt end of all our actions, when we ſo <hi>love our ſelves,</hi> as to <hi>love no man but our ſelves,</hi> according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Every man for himſelf, &amp;c.</hi> when we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>glory,</hi> and the <hi>common good:</hi> but intend our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and our own <hi>private gain</hi> and <hi>intereſt;</hi> when we ſerve <hi>God</hi> upon <hi>politique deſignes;</hi> Of this ſinful ſelf-love the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.21. <hi>For all ſeek their own, and not the things of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And if we had a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow to look into the hearts of moſt people, we ſhould find their hearts made up all of this Idolatrous <hi>ſelf-love.</hi> All their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes are for to promote themſelves. They <hi>monopolize</hi> and <hi>ingroſſe</hi> all to themſelves, as if made for themſelves Where his ſinful ſelf-love <hi>dwels,</hi> there <hi>dwels</hi> no <hi>love to God,</hi> no <hi>love to thy brother,</hi> no <hi>love to Church nor State.</hi> This ſinful ſelf-love is the <hi>Caterpillar</hi> that deſtroyeth Church &amp; Commonwealth. It is from this ſinful ſelf-love that the <hi>publique affairs</hi> drive on ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily, and that <hi>Church-government</hi> is not ſetled, &amp; that our <hi>Covenant</hi> is ſo much neglected Of this ſin I cannot now ſpeak: but when <hi>God</hi> ſhall offer opportunity, I ſhall endeavour to uncaſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or you. In the mean time, the Lord give you grace to hate it as <hi>hell it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96187:88"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
